全體上車
All aboard!
皇家郵政
唐頓莊園
後門
-早  -今天有封特別的
- Morning. - Special one today.
天啊
Blimey.
那是什麼
What have you got there?
就不告訴你
Wouldn't you like to know.
剛到的  老爺
Just arrived, milord.
有一封來自白金漢宮
There's one from Buckingham Palace.
老天爺
Heavens.
但我們必須得截流
But we really need to cut back
直到農場的投資獲得回報
until the farms repay the investment.
而且我們也得為屋頂做好打算
And we must make a plan for the roof.
這對我們的節約大計肯定沒好處
Well, this won't help us to economize.
怎麼了
What is it?
國王和王后要來留宿了
The king and queen are coming to stay.
什麼
What?
在他們的約克郡巡視期間嗎
During their Yorkshire tour?
是的  就待一晚
That's it. Just for a night.
他們要在唐頓住一晚
They'll spend one night at Downton
然後去哈伍德參加舞會
and then go on to Harewood for a ball.
他們在此期間
While they're here,
村裡要舉行約克郡輕騎兵閱兵
there's to be a parade of the Yorkshire Hussars in the village.
亨利能回來嗎
Is there any chance Henry might be back?
恐怕不能
Well, I doubt it.
我會給他發電報
I'll send a telegram.
但芝加哥有場汽車展
But there's a motor show in Chicago
我知道他肯定不能錯過
that I know he cannot chuck.
湯姆  你似乎不怎麼激動呢
Tom, you're keeping your enthusiasm under control.
是那位愛爾蘭愛國者又要冒出來了嗎
Is this the Irish patriot making a reappearance?
我知道你覺得我的看法很好笑
I know you find my opinions highly entertaining.
他們大概要派人來確認
I suppose they'll send people to check that
派特莫太太不是俄國間諜
Mrs. Patmore isn't a Russian spy.
你可以告知樓下嗎  巴羅
Will you tell them downstairs, Barrow?
-我會告訴夫人的  -是  老爺
- I'll see to Her Ladyship. - Yes, milord.
皇家午宴  閱兵  還有一頓晚宴
A royal luncheon, a parade and a dinner?
我可得坐會兒
I'm going to have to sit down.
-那布蘭森先生怎麼辦  -他怎麼了
- Oh, what about Mr. Branson? - What about him?
他不是共和黨人嗎
Well, he's a republican, isn't he?
卡森先生要是過來
Should Mr. Carson look in,
誰都不許在他面前提那個詞
no one is to say that word in front of him.
我贊同布蘭森先生的看法  我也不喜歡國王
I agree with Mr. Branson. I don't like kings, either.
或許這表示我也是共和黨人
I suppose that makes me a republican, too.
英國人可以做共和黨人嗎
Are the English allowed to be?
只有兩周時間準備嗎  天啊
Two weeks to get ready? Golly.
真是殊榮
It's quite an honor.
是啊
It is.
但就我對皇室駕臨的瞭解
But if I know anything about royal visits,
我們得一套套地換衣服了
we will never stop changing our clothes.
我剛去買了一大堆東西
I've just been on a buying spree,
這樣正好
which is good.
韓德利-西摩女士要為我做件舞會裙
Madame Handley-Seymour is making me a ball dress.
-我會叫她加緊進度  -叫她寄來這裡
- I'll get her to hurry it up. - Have her send it here.
-其他事如何  -您知道的
- How are things otherwise? - Oh, you know.
我今天有頓30人的午宴  為了資助救生艇
I've got a luncheon for 30 today in aid of the lifeboats.
還是明天來著
Or is that tomorrow?
反正是為了資助什麼
Anyway, it's in aid of something.
聽上去你還是那麼繁忙
Sounds like business as usual.
那回頭見了  親愛的
I'll see you soon, darling.
你知道我能帶回來
You know I can bring back
我們吃不完的蔬菜
as many vegetables as we could eat.
-我喜歡有事做  -嗯
- Yeah, I like to keep busy. - Yeah.
宅子那邊對消息是什麼反應
How have they taken the news up at the house?
黛西唱起了《馬賽曲》
Daisy's singing "The Marseillaise."
毫不意外
So no surprises there.
怎麼了
What's the matter?
我以為你會高興呢
I thought you'd be pleased.
我是高興
I am pleased.
來訪是無上榮幸
The visit is a great honor.
但皇室成員
But members of the royal and imperial household
要來唐頓
are coming to Downton
而他們肯定已經去過國內最尊貴的大宅
who will have visited the greatest houses in the land.
布萊尼姆  查特斯沃思  阿倫德爾
Blenheim, Chatsworth, Arundel.
巴羅先生清楚他要承擔怎樣的重任嗎
Does Mr. Barrow know what he's taking on?
這跟你有什麼關係
Why should it affect you?
你已經不是當家的了
You're not in charge anymore.
快進來吃午飯  吃完我好回去
Now, come in for your lunch and let me get back.
先生  就這裡了
All right, sir, here we are.
這裡就行了  謝謝
This will do very well. Thank you.
巴格肖夫人  陛下
The Lady Bagshaw, Your Majesty.
好
Good.
等他們來了  我們就去1844房
We'll go to the 1844 Room as soon as they're here.
請坐吧
Do sit down.
我剛拿到了約克郡行程的計畫  陛下
I've just received the plan for the tour of Yorkshire, ma'am.
是  剛定好
Yes. It's just been finalized.
我相信會很愉快的
I think we'll enjoy it.
我不知道我們還要去唐頓莊園住
I didn't realize we would be staying at Downton Abbey.
就一晚
Only for a night.
要看閱兵  吃一頓晚宴
There's to be a parade and a dinner,
然後就去哈伍德看瑪麗公主
and then we go on to Princess Mary at Harewood.
不知我可不可以
I just wondered if I might, perhaps,
直接去哈伍德
go straight to Harewood.
格蘭瑟姆伯爵是我的親戚
Lord Grantham is my cousin,
而兩家...
and the two families have...
有些不睦
fallen out.
至少如果我與他們見了面  可能會吵起來
Or at least we might if I were there in person.
會是為什麼吵起來呢
And what would cause this quarrel?
格蘭瑟姆伯爵的母親認為她兒子應做我的繼承人
Lord Grantham's mother believes her son should be my heir.
老格蘭瑟姆夫人有時是很不依不饒
Old Lady Grantham can be very hard to resist,
我很清楚的
as I am well aware.
是啊  陛下
Exactly, ma'am.
但如果他們的希望註定要落空
But, surely, they need to know
他們也得知道啊
if their hopes are to be disappointed.
真不知他們會喜歡簡單還是高檔的食物
I wish I knew if they like simple food or fancy.
他們肯定不會想吃簡單食物
I can't think they'll want simple food.
就他們那些人  肯定喜歡醬汁
With that sort, don't they like sauces
白醬汁  冰鎮  什麼都抹上奶油吧
and everything velouté and frappé and smothered in cream?
"那些人"  他可是英國國王
"That sort"? He's the King of England.
全世界就一個
There's only one of them in the world.
還"那些人"呢
"That sort," indeed.
別計畫得太詳細
Don't plan too much.
等我們瞭解要求再說
Not until we know what's expected.
我清楚對我的要求  食物
Well, I know what's expected of me-- food.
你也是  黛西  少貧嘴  多幹活兒吧
You, too, Daisy. So less philosophy, more elbow grease.
-布丁好了嗎  -嗯
- Is the pudding ready? - It is.
黛西  把蛋奶酥從烤爐裡拿出來
Oh, Daisy, take the soufflés out of the oven
我去拿眼鏡
while I find me specs.
這國家需要改變
This country needs a shake-up.
你該去競選議員
You should run for parliament.
有何不可  阿斯特夫人不就做到了
Why not? Lady Astor's done it.
所以約克郡的一個廚娘助手就肯定能緊隨其後嗎
And so an under-cook from Yorkshire is bound to follow her.
你總得有大夢想嘛
Well, you've got to have big dreams.
但你有大夢想嗎  安迪
But do you have big dreams, Andy?
我沒惹你生氣吧
I've not offended you, have I?
-為什麼這麼問  -首先
- Why do you say that? - Well, for a start,
你都不提我們婚禮的事了
you never talk about the wedding anymore.
我們準備好了再結婚嘛
We'll get wed when we're good and ready and not before.
但是  我是準備好了
But, you see, I am ready.
快把那個端上去  待會兒要塌了
Take those up before they collapse.
莫德•巴格肖要來唐頓嗎
Maud Bagshaw is coming to Downton?
對  作為王后的侍女
Yes, as the queen's lady-in-waiting.
老天爺
Oh, my goodness.
為何這麼驚訝  她是什麼人
Why so surprised? Who is she?
她是你父親的親戚
Well, she's a cousin of your father's.
我們稍後再說吧
We'll-we'll discuss it later.
您可別搞得大家下不來台
You're not to make things awkward.
準備得如何了
How's it all going?
都在瑪麗掌控之中了
Well, Mary's got it under control.
才沒有  要做的事太多了
Hardly. There's so much to do.
我們來時  看到在草地上丈量的人是誰
Who were those men measuring on the green as we came past?
他們在搭建閱兵時王后要站的講臺
They're building the dais for the queen at the parade.
-真令人期待  -感覺是浪費錢呢
- Oh, how exciting. - Seems rather a waste of money.
又來了
Here we go.
王室不就該如此嗎
Isn't that what the monarchy's for?
用他們的威嚴和魅力
To brighten the lives of the nation
為國民的生活添彩
with stateliness and glamour?
用丁尼生的話說"仁心貴於冠冕
To quote Tennyson, "Kind hearts are more than coronets,
信念勝於血統"
And simple faith than Norman blood."
你有足夠的陳詞濫調撐過這次到訪嗎
Will you have enough clichés to get you through the visit?
如果想不出了  我就來找你
If not, I'll come to you.
謝謝  巴羅
Thank you, Barrow.
現在告訴我們巴格肖夫人的事吧
And, now, you were gonna tell us about Lady Bagshaw.
她是個遠親嗎
Is she a very distant cousin?
不是  她父親是我的祖伯父
No. Her father was my great uncle.
那我怎麼沒聽說過她
Then why have I never heard of her?
因為她選擇斷絕了跟家族的關係
Because she chose to cut herself off from the family.
-您知道為什麼嗎  -可能吧
- Do you know the reason? - Maybe.
我認為她有意剝奪你父親的
See, I believe she means to cheat your father
合法繼承權
of his rightful inheritance.
她自己沒孩子
She has no children.
而你父親是她關係最近的親戚
Your father is her nearest relation.
可不許為難她
I won't have her put on the spot.
你在謀劃什麼
You're plotting something.
你有種狡猾的[馬基雅弗利]眼神
I see a Machiavellian look in your eye.
馬基雅弗利向來被低估
Machiavelli is frequently underrated.
他有很多品質呢
He had many qualities.
卡利古拉也有  可不都是好品質
So did Caligula, not all of them charming.
古羅馬暴君
您想幹什麼  奶奶
What are you up to, Granny?
最好是能讓莫德將你父親視為
Well, ideally, I would like Maud to see your father
她沒能有的兒子
as the son she never had.
那她能成為我沒能有的母親嗎
Will she be the mother I never had?
諷刺是最低級的智慧
Sarcasm is the lowest form of wit.
-你好  -莫斯利先生
- Hello. - Mr. Molesley.
這麼晚了還出來
It's very late for you to be out.
是真的嗎
Is it true?
什麼是真的嗎  莫斯利先生
Is what true, Mr. Molesley?
貝克韋爾先生說  您告訴他
Mr. Bakewell said that you'd warned him
皇室要來造訪
that there was to be a royal visit.
這下我知道有秘密不能告訴誰了
Well, now I know who not to trust with a secret.
我們居然能有如此榮幸
That we should deserve such honor.
你怎麼也這樣  我好失望
Not you, too. I am disappointed.
-別理她  -你說我能不能
- Ignore her. - I wonder, do you think
被允許再穿一次號服
I might be allowed to slip on my livery again?
學校能放你走嗎
Would the school let you?
他們肯定會為此准我假的  肯定的
Oh, they'll give me time for this, I promise.
等我們知道了要求再說吧
Let's wait till we know our orders.
怎麼樣  巴羅先生
What about it, Mr. Barrow?
你能允許我為國王和王后服務嗎
Will you let me wait upon my king and queen?
這...
Well...
叫我們了
That's us.
再見了  莫斯利先生
Good night, Mr. Molesley.
等我們完事了  是我去接約翰尼
When we're done, shall I fetch Johnny
-還是你去  -我去吧
- or will you? - I can fetch him.
太讓人激動了
How exciting.
-謝謝  -他們都瘋了
- Thank you. - They're all mental.
為了我們根本不認識的一對男女這麼大驚小怪
All this fuss for a man and woman we don't even know.
別管那個了  我想跟你說
No, never mind that. I wanted to tell you.
我想到了一些你婚禮上可以做的菜
I've had some ideas about what to serve at your wedding.
別老提那茬了
Stop going on about my wedding.
我們只剩幾天了
We've only a few days left,
我問過夫人  她同意了
so I spoke to Her Ladyship, and she's agreed
平時的規矩要暫時改改
our normal rules should be suspended.
有主人家在用的房間我們不打掃
We won't clean a room if a family member is using it,
但除此之外  沒有其他限制了
but, otherwise, all restrictions are lifted.
一切細節  不管多小  都要顧及到
No detail should be left undone, however small.
週四之前  這宅子裡
I want every surface in this house
所有地方都要亮得發光
to gleam and sparkle by Thursday.
天啊
Blimey.
大家可以注意一下嗎
Can I have your attention, please?
今天下午
For this afternoon,
陛下的管家  威爾森先生
Their Majesties' butler, Mr. Wilson,
將從雷比城堡過來
will be coming over from Raby Castle
並會帶一位貼身女僕和一位貼身男僕來
with a lady's maid and a valet.
向我們傳達指示嗎
To give us our instructions?
那皇室僕人要我們服侍嗎
With the royal servants, are we to wait on them?
這就得聽他們怎麼說了
That is what will be made clear.
我可不要服侍貼身男僕和女僕
I won't be waiting on any valets and lady's maids,
多謝了
thank you very much.
我們先別上火
Before we get hot under the collar,
-等等看他們怎麼說嘛  -阿門
- let's just wait and see what they have to say. - Amen.
布蘭森先生
Mr. Branson.
有什麼需要嗎  先生
Can I help you, sir?
我其實是來找你的
It's really you I came to see.
-需要我做什麼嗎  您是...  -切特伍德
- Well, how can I help you, Mister...? - Chetwode.
切特伍德少校
Major Chetwode.
您是布蘭森先生吧  格蘭瑟姆伯爵的女婿
Am I right you're Mr. Branson, Lord Grantham's son-in-law?
是的
I am.
報紙上說  國王和王后來
The, uh... the papers tell me the king and queen
約克郡期間會在唐頓莊園小住
will be staying at Downton Abbey during their tour of Yorkshire.
如果報紙上說了  那肯定是真的
Well, if it's in the papers, it must be true.
是啊  真是榮幸
Yes. Great honor.
但作為愛爾蘭人  你可能不這麼覺得
Although, as an Irishman, you may feel differently.
我至少也知道這是對我岳父母的肯定
I know when my parents-in-law have been paid a compliment.
而且還會進行閱兵  是吧
Well, there's to be a military parade, I gather.
你對此有什麼看法
How do you... how do you feel about that?
什麼意思  我有什麼看法
What do you mean, how do I feel?
你並沒說你是否支持他們
Only you didn't say whether you support them,
國王和王后
the... king and queen.
我支持格蘭瑟姆伯爵
I support Lord Grantham.
很好
Very neat.
那我們後會有期了  布蘭森先生
Until we meet again, Mr. Branson.
巴羅  他們說你在這裡
Barrow. They said you'd be in here.
天啊  很高興有需要時
Heavens. We can still put on quite a show
我們還能一展風采
when we need to, I'm glad to see.
都清理過了嗎
Has it all been cleaned?
一切都多少做了個大概  小姐
More or less everything's been done to a basic level, milady.
但最後的調整還沒做
But we haven't done the final buffing-up.
為什麼沒
Why not?
我是在等陛下的管家
I was waiting for Their Majesties' butler.
我想問問他該在桌上擺什麼
I thought I'd ask his advice on what to use on the table.
是嗎
Really?
我們自家的桌上擺什麼  我們不能決定嗎
Can't we decide what we lay on our own dining table?
前門鈴  巴羅先生
Front doorbell, Mr. Barrow.
去吧
Please, go.
是  小姐
Milady.
你好  威爾森先生
Greetings, Mr. Wilson.
歡迎來到唐頓莊園
Welcome to Downton Abbey.
這邊請  威爾森先生
This way, Mr. Wilson.
皇室管家好嚇人
The royal butler's terribly scary.
巴羅活像看到眼鏡蛇的兔子
Barrow looked like a rabbit in front of a cobra.
天啊  需要我下去嗎
Oh, dear. Should I go down?
他們有數的
They know what they're doing.
是嗎  他們的工作嚴重滯後
Do they? They're hideously behind.
藍房的地毯上有塊弄不掉的污漬
There's a mark on the Blue Room carpet we can't shift.
我也沒給閱兵找到椅子
I have no chairs for the parade.
男僕的事也還沒定下來
And we haven't even decided on the footmen.
如果沒人上來服侍  我自己再倒杯茶吧
I'm going to have another cup, if no one's coming up to serve.
真不錯
This is nice.
瑪麗公主邀請我們明天去哈伍德喝下午茶
Princess Mary wants us for tea tomorrow at Harewood.
我還有一堆事呢
I've got so much to do.
不知這是不是表示這對年輕夫婦
I wonder if that means the young couple
住進了大宅裡
have taken over the big house.
他們可算不上"年輕夫婦"
They're hardly "the young couple."
至少他不算
Well, he isn't, anyway.
我一直覺得她很害羞
She always seems quite shy to me.
害羞的皇室成員
A shy royal?
這不自相矛盾嗎
Is that an oxymoron?
反正  我們要去
Anyway, we're going.
好吧
Right.
我會回雷比城堡  然後週四在陛下
I will return to Raby Castle and come back to Downton
到唐頓莊園之前先趕來
in advance of Their Majesties on Thursday.
但國王陛下的貼身男僕  艾理斯先生
But His Majesty's valet, Mr. Ellis,
和王后陛下的服裝師  勞頓小姐
and Her Majesty's dresser, Miss Lawton,
會住下  希望不會不便
will stay on, if that is convenient.
他們也可以去村裡住
Or they can put up in the village.
不  我們會給他們安排房間的
No, we'll find them rooms.
還有主廚科貝特先生
Then Monsieur Courbet, the chef...
不好意思
E-Excuse me.
-主廚科貝特先生嗎  -對
- Mr. Courbet, the chef? - That's right.
我們希望你能準備好廚房
We'd be very grateful if you could make the kitchens ready.
那我要訂購什麼呢
So, what should I order?
不用  他會把東西都帶來
Nothing. He will bring it all.
我們不做飯嗎
And we don't cook any of the food?
為僕人做飯就好
Cook for the servants.
科貝特先生不會有那個時間的
Monsieur Courbet won't have time for that.
這樣啊
Oh, I see.
那真是值得期待呢
That is something to look forward to.
冷靜點  派特莫太太
Calm yourself, Mrs. Patmore.
如果這是這種事的規矩...
If it's the way these things are done...
韋伯太太和四位男僕會在
Mrs. Webb and four footmen will arrive
前一天隨科貝特先生到來
with Monsieur Courbet the day before.
這位韋伯太太
Who is this...
是嗎  她是誰
Mrs. Webb, is it?
她是女管家
She is the housekeeper.
她還會帶來兩位女僕
She will also bring two maids with her.
女管家
The housekeeper?
就是陛下下榻期間
While Their Majesties are here.
還有女僕呢
And the maids?
她們負責鋪床
They will make the beds,
清理浴室  什麼的
clean the bathrooms-- that sort of thing.
這樣啊
I see.
那我和我的女僕就不參與準備工作了嗎
So, my maids and I will not be involved in the preparations?
就是說下榻期間  你是管家
You mean, during the stay, you'll be the butler, and...
不好意思  我可不是管家
Excuse me. I am not a butler.
我是國王侍從長
I am the king's Page of the Backstairs.
那我們的下人就無事可做嗎
So, our staff has nothing to do?
他們肯定能幫上忙的
I'm sure they can be useful.
但如果主廚  貼身男僕  女僕都在這裡
But how can they eat and get dressed at Raby Castle
他們要怎麼在雷比城堡吃飯更衣
if the chef and the valet and the maid are all here?
所有僕人都有兩個
We have two of each.
主貼身男僕和主服裝師
The principal valet and the principal dresser
會先于陛下趕到
will arrive in advance of Their Majesties,
同行的還有掌馬官  侍女
who bring an equerry, a lady-in-waiting,
兩位警探  和兩個司機
two detectives and two chauffeurs.
另一個主廚從雷比去哈伍德
The other chef goes from Raby to Harewood.
有四位男僕隨他走  另外四位來這裡
Four footmen go with him, and the other four come here.
你們都懂了嗎
Do you all understand me?
你總不能在王后面前
You can hardly heckle Lady Bagshaw
為難巴格肖夫人
in front of the queen.
我只是想避免犯罪
Well, I'm just trying to prevent a crime.
-誰說這是犯罪了  -我說
- Who says it's a crime? - I do.
你在這事上就是專家嗎
Oh, and you're an expert in the matter?
我在什麼事上都是專家
I am an expert in every matter.
你肯定能猜到
You must have some idea
她為何不希望羅伯特做她的繼承人吧
why she doesn't want Robert as her heir.
我完全想不出
I have none.
他是她最近的親屬
He is her closest relative.
布朗普頓在她家流傳三個世紀了
The family have held Brompton for three centuries.
但她想捐給誰呢
But she wants to give it to who?
慈善機構嗎
Charity?
還是寵物機構
The dogs' home?
我倒以為
Well, I would have thought
家裡要操心的事夠多了
the family had enough to worry about.
那不是重點
That's not the point.
好吧
Well, very well.
我們得努力探明她的理由
We must try and discover her reasons.
能有什麼理由呢
Well, what possible reasons can there be?
那就是我想知道的
Well, that's what I intend to find out.
-卡森  -小姐
- Carson. - Oh, milady.
請進
Please come in.
真是榮幸
This is an honor.
我不想給你添麻煩  但我需要你説明  卡森
I don't want to be a nuisance, but I need your help, Carson.
巴羅實在難擔重任
Barrow just isn't up to the task.
-什麼意思  小姐  -他不肯清理銀器
- Milady? - He won't clean the silver.
-或者說他不肯讓安德魯清理銀器  -什麼
- Or he won't let Andrew clean it. - What?
他說那個什麼侍從長
He says the page of the... thingummy
-會選擇用哪件銀器  -這樣啊
- will choose which pieces to use. - I see.
事實上  他暈暈乎乎的
The truth is, he's in a sort of trance.
你願意幫我嗎
Won't you help me?
我感覺自己的擔子好重
I feel I'm pushing a rock uphill.
我早上就去  小姐  您別擔心
I'll be there in the morning, milady. Don't you worry.
你太好了  卡森  別的不說了
You're a treasure, Carson. That's all there is to say.
我自己出去了
I'll see myself out.
你就是沒法對她說不
You could never refuse her anything.
那巴羅先生怎麼辦
And what about Mr. Barrow?
巴羅先生要不高興就得受著
Mr. Barrow can like it or lump it.
那他肯定是得受著了
Then I'm afraid he'll lump it.
我們在樓上晚餐後用餐
We have supper after the upstairs dinner,
你的時間肯定夠
so you've plenty of time.
謝謝
Thanks.
兩個貼身男僕怎麼工作啊
How does it work with two valets?
我為國王準備在唐頓穿的
Well, I prepare His Majesty's clothes
衣服和制服
and uniforms for Downton.
然後等米勒先生到了
Then, when Mr. Miller arrives,
我再把在哈伍德要用的東西備好
I get the stuff for Harewood ready.
然後我回倫敦  為他們的歸來做準備
Then I head back to London and prepare for their return.
一環扣一環
It all overlaps.
所以是米勒先生為國王更衣
So, Mr. Miller's the one who actually dresses the king?
除非他生病  那就是我來
Unless he's ill. Then it's me.
他常生病嗎
Is he often ill?
不
No.
真不像話  他們高高在上地提出要求
I think it's rubbish. They impose, they demand,
現在我們在自己家裡卻無所適從
and now we're to be made nothing in our own house.
我不否認  真是讓人失望
It's very disappointing, I won't deny it.
這水不怎麼熱
This water's not too hot.
他們都在洗澡嗎
Have they all been having baths?
我怎麼知道
How should I know?
巴羅先生  你不該跟老爺說說嗎
Mr. Barrow, don't you think you should speak to His Lordship?
-說什麼  -這不像話吧
- About what? - Well, it's not right, surely,
我們受到這樣的羞辱
for us to be humiliated in this way.
他又能怎樣呢
Well, what could he do about it?
難道皇室下榻的時候
Is the staff always ridden over roughshod
僕人總這樣被踐踏嗎
whenever royalty come to stay?
他們幹嗎隨身帶那麼多僕人
Why do they bring so many servants with them?
或許是因為他們要跑遍全郡
Maybe it's because they go from house to house around the county
所以想確保一切按他們的喜歡的方式來
and they need to know things are done the way they like.
難道我們就做不好嗎
As if we couldn't manage that.
我們不是足球  貝茨先生
We're not footballs, Mr. Bates,
我們不該被這樣踢走
and we don't deserve a kicking.
但我們怎麼跟巴羅說
But what are we to say to Barrow?
畢竟  他沒做錯什麼
After all, he's done nothing wrong.
他根本什麼都沒做  問題就在這裡
He's done nothing at all. That's the problem.
但這似乎很不公平
But it feels very unfair.
這樣啊
Oh, I see.
這就來了
So it's now.
我已叫人去喊巴羅先生來了  老爺
I've sent down for Mr. Barrow to join us, milord.
您找我  老爺
You wanted to see me, milord?
卡森先生
Mr. Carson!
您怎麼來了
What brings you here?
是這樣的
Well, this is the thing.
皇室下榻期間  卡森會搬回來住
Carson is going to move back into the house for the royal visit.
什麼
What?
您要回來做管家嗎
You are coming back here as butler
我才是管家
when I am the butler here?
是的  這...
Yes, uh, that is...
我可以問問這事謀劃多久了嗎  老爺
Can I ask how long this has been planned, milord?
倒也說不上是謀劃
Well, I wouldn't say it's been exactly planned.
因為我不太懂
Because I don't quite understand
這下我怎麼辦
where it leaves me.
-你可以算是...  -如果您允許
- Well, you can be a sort of... - With your permission,
我不想"算是"什麼  老爺
I'd prefer not to be a "sort of" anything, milord.
如果有必要
I will surrender my position
造訪期間我會讓位
for the duration of the visit, if I must,
等陛下離開後  再繼續為您服務
and serve you again when Their Majesties have gone,
如果這是您的意思
if you so wish.
-請不要認為...  -對了
- Please don't think that... - By the way,
鍋爐出了問題  沒有熱水了
the boiler's playing up, and there's no hot water.
天啊  這可好
God, that's all we need.
巴羅
Now, Barrow...
別擔心  水管工很快就能修好  小姐
Not to worry. The plumber will soon have it mended, milady,
今晚和明早我們用水壺把熱水
and we'll bring water jugs up to the bedrooms tonight
拿上樓就好
and in the morning.
這又不難
It can't be that hard.
三百年來不都這麼幹的
We did it for 300 years.
謝謝  卡森
Thank you, Carson.
真是順利
Well, that went well.
您要解雇他嗎
Will you sack him?
不  事實上  我還覺得挺有趣
No. As a matter of fact, I was quite interested.
我以前可從沒覺得他是個有原則的人
I never thought of him as a man of principle before.
我得告訴他
I'll have to tell him
我只是來為僕人採購的
I'm only ordering for the servants' hall.
我恐怕是讓他白抱希望了
I'm afraid I've got his hopes up.
正說著你呢
Speak of the devil.
快進來
Come in, come in.
我剛剛還說  你肯定想確認訂單
I was just saying you'll be wanting to finalize the order.
是嗎
Were you, indeed?
真的  村裡的人
Honestly, no one in the village
-張口閉口都在說這個  -當然了
- can talk about anything else. - Of course.
我知道這有點自作主張
Oh, now, I know it's a bit of a liberty,
但我列出了所有你最喜歡做的菜的原料
but I've made a list of all the ingredients of your favorite dishes.
這麼多年了  我早背熟了
I know them well enough after all these years.
但有些東西還得另買
But some things will have to be brought in,
所以我們真得抓緊了
so we should really get on with it.
我感謝你的一切努力  貝克韋爾先生
Well, I appreciate everything you've done, Mr. Bakewell...
我都要樂開花了
My heart is fit to burst,
真的
I don't mind telling you.
我的小店為國王陛下提供了食物
I shall have fed the king-emperor from my own shop.
只可惜我父親看不到了
If only my father were alive.
不然他肯定會很為我驕傲
He'd be so proud of me. He would.
他肯定本來就為你驕傲的  貝克韋爾先生
Well, I-I'm sure he'd be proud of you anyway, Mr. Bakewell.
不不  這可不一樣
Oh, no, no, not like this, no.
這是我職業生涯的巔峰
This is the peak of my career.
也是我人生的巔峰
Well, the peak of my life, really.
大家都好嫉妒
Everyone's so jealous.
我在我覺得你會需要的東西旁打了勾
Oh, now, I've put ticks next to the ones I think you'll go for.
-是這樣...  -我猜午餐大概是
- Now, the thing is... - I'm guessing the luncheon
12個人左右
will be for around a dozen.
當然了  晚宴要更盛大
Of course, the dinner will be larger.
30個人差不多吧
Let's say 30 or thereabouts?
如果我說錯了請您糾正
You'll correct me if I'm wrong.
-是這樣...  -您說對了  貝克韋爾先生
- Well, you see... - You're not wrong, Mr. Bakewell.
但如果人數有變我們再告訴您
But we'll say if the numbers change.
奶油水果蛋白餅不太實際
The pavlova's not realistic.
還是俄式奶油蛋糕更保險
We'd be safer with a charlotte russe.
大部分能提前準備
We can do most of the work before.
我還能服侍他們
And I shall be serving!
想想看啊
Think of that!
我跟一個跟威爾士王子跳過舞的
I've danced with a man who's danced with a girl
女孩跳過舞的男人跳過舞
Who's danced with the Prince of Wales
-我激動瘋了  -快停下  莫斯利先生
- I'm crazy with excitement - No. Stop it, Mr. Molesley.
完全樂壞了
Completely off the rails.
我的供應商都激動極了
All of my suppliers are so excited.
派特莫太太
Mrs. Patmore,
我將永遠對您感激不盡
I shall never be able to thank you enough,
哪怕我活到一百歲
not if I live to be 100.
我覺得自己是個騙子
I feel like a liar.
我該回去
I should go back.
讓村裡人把你當成卑微的
And lower yourself to a kitchen skivvy
廚房女傭嗎
in the eyes of the village?
更別說讓貝克韋爾先生難過一年了
Never mind ruining Mr. Bakewell's year.
你不能這麼做
You'll do no such thing.
沒帶女僕  沒帶貼身男僕
No maid. No valet.
甚至沒帶保姆
No nanny, even.
都1927年了
It's 1927.
我們是現代人
We're modern folk.
保姆會照顧瑪麗戈德
Nanny will take care of Marigold.
安娜會照顧你
And Anna can look after you.
是嗎  真的嗎
Really? Can she?
當然了
Of course.
就像以前一樣  奶奶和伊澤貝爾都來了
Just like the old days. Granny's here, and Isobel,
我們下午還要去拜訪瑪麗公主
and we're paying a call this afternoon on Princess Mary.
我的新舞會裙到了嗎
Has my new ball dress arrived?
還沒呢  會來的
Not yet, but it will.
你好  瑪麗
Hello, Mary.
你好嗎
How are you?
你為王后陛下工作多久了  勞頓小姐
How long have you worked for Her Majesty, Miss Lawton?
-六年  -真有趣
- Six years. - How interesting.
能擔此大任  你一定是個技藝高超的女裁縫
I expect you're a skilled needlewoman for that job.
至少沒人對我的手藝有過不滿
Well, I've had no complaints.
我曾師從露西爾女士
I trained under Madame Lucile.
王后陛下想要個專業的裁縫
Her Majesty wanted a professional dressmaker.
於是便找了你嗎
And they found you?
是我的聲名讓他們找到了我
My reputation found me.
快點  你們兩個  快3點了
Come on, you two. It's nearly 3:00.
我們需要做好準備
We ought to get ready.
-公主會參加閱兵嗎  -謝謝
- Will the princess be at the parade? - Thank you.
-他們夫婦都會的  -我們說好幾點到
- They both will. - What time are they expecting us?
我一直覺得瑪麗公主非常悲傷
I always find her rather sad, Princess Mary.
她是皇室成員
Well, she is royal.
皇室女子本就不該隨意露齒大笑
Royal women are not meant to grin like Cheshire cats.
那也不必顯得慘兮兮的啊
Well, they don't have to look miserable.
是你覺得她看上去慘
Well, to you, she looks miserable.
我覺得她看上去非常高貴
To me, she looks dignified.
這說明了很多問題  不是嗎
Doesn't that say it all?
看到你來了  真讓我安心  卡森
How comforting to see you here, Carson.
是什麼促使你又肩負起了從前的重任呢
What prompted you to take up the flaming sword again?
我覺得我該去到能發揮最大用處的地方  夫人
I felt I should go where I could do the most good, milady.
這句明智之言適用我們所有人
Wise words for all of us.
公主殿下在裡面
Her Royal Highness is here.
赫克瑟姆侯爵夫人
The Marchioness of Hexham,
格蘭瑟姆伯爵夫人
the Countess of Grantham,
以及瑪麗•塔伯特小姐
the Lady Mary Talbot.
見過公主殿下
Your Royal Highness.
請坐吧  格蘭瑟姆夫人
Please, sit down, Lady Grantham.
我父母的到訪一定讓你們手忙腳亂吧
I suppose you're in turmoil because of my parents' visit.
我非常同情你們
I do sympathize.
我們可不需要對您多說
We don't need to explain it to you.
不要刷新漆
Just don't paint anything.
他們很討厭新油漆的氣味
They're sick of the smell of new paint.
但願這條忠告不算太遲
I hope it's not too late.
您現在住在這裡嗎  殿下
Are you living here now, ma'am?
不  我們還是住在戈爾茲伯勒
No. No, we're still at Goldsborough.
但哈伍德伯爵的身體不太好  所以...
But Lord Harewood's not well, so...
我們前來準備到訪和舞會的事宜
we've come to run the visit and the ball.
你們好啊
Oh, hello.
你們好  親愛的
Hello, my darlings.
你們還好嗎
How have you been?
今天開不開心啊
Have you been having a lovely day?
什麼事
Yes?
今天是你的幸運日
This is your lucky day.
我是新來的水管工  托尼•薩利克
I'm the new plumber, Tony Sellick.
是啊  對了
Oh, yes. Right.
我帶你去鍋爐房吧
Well, I'd better show you where the boiler is.
你去哪
Where are you off to?
這是水管工薩利克先生
This is Mr. Sellick, the plumber.
我帶他去鍋爐房
I'm taking him to the boiler house.
-我來帶吧  -不  不用了
- I'll do it. - No, you're all right.
跟派特莫太太說一聲我去哪了就行
Just tell Mrs. Patmore where I am.
週四務必也把孩子們都帶來
Please bring the boys on Thursday.
真是好極了
Oh, how lovely.
孩子們怎麼在這裡
Why are the children in here?
我們剛回來  他們想...
We just got back, and they wanted to...
6點前他們是不允許進客廳的
They're not allowed in the drawing room before 6:00.
我知道  老爺
I know, milord.
-但他們...  -帶他們去樓上
- But they... - Take them upstairs.
今晚別再把他們帶下來了
And don't bring them down again tonight.
-是  老爺  -但他們只是...
- Yes, milord. - But they were only...
謝謝你  保姆
Thank you, Nanny.
-求你了  保姆  -不行  我們得走了
- Please, Nanny? - No, we're going.
還記得格蘭瑟姆夫人和她的女兒們吧
You remember Lady Grantham and her daughters?
格蘭瑟姆夫人
Lady Grantham.
她們希望我們帶兒子們去參加閱兵
They want us to bring the boys to the parade.
不行  他們只會惹人煩
No. They'd only cause a ruckus.
我們希望你們二人
We were hoping you would both
當晚都能留下用餐  拉塞爾斯伯爵
stay for dinner that night, Lord Lascelles.
不  恐怕不行
No, I'm afraid not.
那...
Well...
我就不打擾你們了
I'll leave you to it.
那你開工吧  我就不打擾了
Well, I suppose I better let you get started,
-我走了  -你不打算祝我好運嗎
- so I'll be on me way. - Aren't you gonna wish me luck?
看你的樣子可不需要我的祝願  薩利克先生
You don't look as if you need me to wish you luck, Mr. Sellick.
也不需要任何人的祝願
Or anyone else, for that matter.
你可不知道我需要什麼
You don't know what I need.
我也不想知道
And I don't intend to find out.
需要再次修剪草坪嗎
Do we need to cut the grass again?
他們明天早上會修剪的
They're doing it tomorrow morning.
你好  布蘭森先生
Hello, Mr. Branson.
在為迎接國王夫婦做準備啊
Getting ready for Their Majesties, I see.
沒錯  這是赫克瑟姆侯爵
That's right. This is Lord Hexham.
這位是切特伍德少校
May I present Major Chetwode.
你是來參加閱兵的嗎
Are you here for the parade?
正是  我在旅館住下了
I am. I'm staying at the pub.
-侯爵大人  -失陪
- Milord? - Excuse me.
還是說  你其實是來盯著我的
Or are you here to keep an eye on me?
我倒是希望你能帶我參加儀式
I was rather hoping you'd be my guide for the ceremony.
你想喝一杯嗎
Would you like a drink?
我稍後來找你
I'll join you in a minute.
好樣的
Well, well done.
-他是誰  -我也不知道
- Who's he? - I don't really know.
軍方的人吧  也可能是公職人員
Army, perhaps. Or maybe a civil servant.
但我會跟他一起喝酒
But I'll drink with him
努力讓他安下心
and try and put his mind at rest.
他有何目的
What does he want?
或許只是想確保我不再是過去的那個我了
Maybe to make sure I'm a leopard who has changed his spots.
你呢  小姐
What about you, milady?
-都準備好了嗎  -沒有
- Is everything ready? - No.
我的心跳得厲害
And my heart is pounding.
對了  你看到客廳裡
By the way, have you seen the silver box
壁爐邊桌子上的那個銀盒子了嗎
from the table by the fire in the drawing room?
奶奶以前總在裡面放紙牌
My grandmother used to keep playing cards in it.
我知道是哪個
I know the one.
-不見了嗎  -是的
- Is it missing? - Yes.
壁爐架上的小丘比特也不見了
And so is the little cupid from the mantelshelf.
一定是拿到樓下去清潔了
Oh, they must have been taken downstairs for cleaning.
我正要去找您  小姐
I was just coming to you, milady.
別擔心  我沒事
Oh, don't worry. I'm fine.
-沒別的事我先告退了  小姐  -沒事了
- If that's all, milady? - I suppose.
你拿得動水壺和臉盆嗎
Can you manage the jug and basin?
還是太重了
Or are they too heavy?
不  我拿得動
No, no, I can do it.
鍋爐怎麼樣了
Oh, how's the boiler?
他們肯定能儘快修好
I'm sure they'll fix it soon.
伯蒂剛才跟湯姆在一起
Bertie was with Tom earlier.
你說湯姆不會企圖搗亂吧
You don't think Tom would ever try to make trouble?
你怎麼會這麼說
Why do you say that?
伯蒂說有軍隊的人
Well, Bertie says there's some army type
在監視他
who has him under surveillance.
湯姆喜歡嚇人  僅此而已
Tom likes to shock, that's all.
他絕不會背叛這個家  絕對不會
He'd never be disloyal to this family. Never.
我們下樓吧
Shall we go down?
好  走吧
Yes, let's.
於是我跟她說
So, I said to her,
"聽著  小姐
"Listen, lady,
這裡還有個小傢伙需要轉動呢"
there's a little one here who still needs turning."
注意點  薩利克先生
Careful. Mr. Sellick,
黛西聽了會害羞的
you'll make Daisy blush.
我可沒那麼容易害羞
Takes more than that to make me blush.
-喝了吧  -你應得的
- Now, get that down you. - You deserve that.
-很晚了  -我得修完
- It's very late. - Well, I've got to get it done.
而且我不介意長時間工作
And I don't mind long hours.
我打算自己開店單幹
I, uh, mean to build me own business,
那就不可能朝九晚五了
and you can't do that working 9:00 to 5:00.
這些水壺沉死我了
These water jugs nearly killed me.
我們以前是怎麼做到的
How did we manage in the old days?
也許以前的人比較強壯
Well, maybe people were tougher then.
也許他們對生活的期望少一些
Maybe they expected less from life.
我對生活可有很多期望
Well, I expect a lot from life.
我也是  而且我打算實現它們
So do I. And I mean to have it, too.
你還在啊
Are you still here?
薩利克先生為了我們
Mr. Sellick's been working hard
辛苦工作了好幾個小時  安迪
for hours for our benefit, Andy.
那他該回家了
Then it's time he went home.
開胃菜準備好了嗎
Is the savory ready?
端走吧
Take this.
他說得對  新水泵早上9點差不多能到
He's right. The new pump should arrive around 9:00.
-到時我再來  -我們也會在的
- I'll be here. - So will we.
再見
Ta-ra.
剛才是媽媽打來  她在倫敦
That was Mama. She's in London.
-她在羅斯孟德家留宿  -不可能吧
- She's staying with Rosamund. - She can't be.
她跟我們一起吃午飯時可隻字未提
She was here for lunch. She didn't say anything.
她今天下午去的
She went up this afternoon.
她明天就回來  所以我邀請了她來喝茶
She'll be back tomorrow, so I've asked her to come for tea.
你務必勸她別去糾纏莫德•巴格肖
You must persuade her to leave Maud Bagshaw alone.
我想就算是媽媽
I don't believe even Mama
也不會在國王面前尋釁吧
will pick a quarrel in front of the king.
不知道他能否早點來
I wonder if he can come early.
你激動嗎
Are you excited?
有一點  你呢
I am a bit. Are you?
如果我承認會不會很庸俗
Would it be common to admit it?
對美國人來說不會
Not to an American.
他們到了  卡森先生
Here we go, Mr. Carson.
我來處理
Leave this to me.
我是科貝特先生
I am Monsieur Courbet.
這位是女管家  韋伯太太
And this is Mrs. Webb, the housekeeper.
沿著這條路
Follow that path,
就能走到廚房院子
and it'll take you into the kitchen courtyard.
我說了  我是科貝特先生
I said, I am Monsieur Courbet,
國王王后陛下的主廚
chef to Their Majesties.
幹得好  查理
Well done, Charlie.
一開始就奠定了基調
Always start as you mean to go on.
這邊請  先生們
This way, gentlemen.
-勞頓小姐  -我就是到處看看
- Miss Lawton? - I was just looking round.
這莊園很美
It's a beautiful house.
你見過很多更美的
You've seen many that are finer.
我是來拿手套的
That's what I came for.
但我們其實不該進這屋
But we shouldn't be in here, really.
準備好與野蠻人作戰
Prepare for your battle with the barbarians.
你  這個放哪裡
You. Uh, where can I put this?
別惹我
Don't tempt me.
我們在洗滌室騰出了一些空間
We've cleared some space in the scullery.
還有那個櫥櫃
And that cupboard.
真是小題大做
What a lot of fuss over nothing.
跟貝克韋爾先生訂的東西呢
Well, where's our order from Mr. Bakewell?
跟我來
Follow me.
你一個人怎麼做到的
Well, how did you manage it?
一個園丁幫我搬進來的  沒讓人看見
A gardener helped me carry everything in, so no one saw.
或許可以賣掉這些東西
I suppose you could sell the lot
然後拿得來的錢付給貝克韋爾先生
and use the money to pay Mr. Bakewell.
別擔心  等客人走了
Don't worry. They can eat it gradual
他們能慢慢吃完
when the visit's over.
弄好了  派特莫太太
It's done, Mrs. Patmore.
新水泵裝好了
The new pump's installed.
大英雄萬歲
Hail the conquering hero.
你該告訴休斯太太
It's Mrs. Hughes you should be telling.
或卡森先生  而不是她們
Or Mr. Carson. Not them.
沒關係  薩利克先生
It's all right, Mr. Sellick.
我們會轉告他們  謝謝你
We'll see the news gets through. Thanks.
我都不會喂給我的狗吃
I would not feed it to my dog!
但我不需要你幫忙  休斯太太
But I don't need your help, Mrs. Hughes.
我就想知道國王王后陛下睡哪
I just want to know where Their Majesties are sleeping
好讓斯廷森小姐準備好房間
so Miss Stinson can prepare the rooms.
那我帶你去  韋伯太太
Then I will show you, Mrs. Webb,
因為如果沒有我幫你
because, without my help,
你是找不到地方的
you will not find them.
這種事總這樣嗎
Is it always like this?
皇室造訪就像湖上的天鵝
A royal visit is like a swan on a lake.
上面看是優雅和平靜  下面得拼命劃水
Grace and serenity above, demented kicking down below.
我真想偷個閑
I wish I could get away.
等米勒先生到了  我明晚能放假
I've got tomorrow night off when Mr. Miller arrives.
我還說好去看媽媽
Told my mum I'd look in.
你跟我一起去約克吧
Why don't you come to York with me?
-我們喝一杯  -你去吧
- We could have a drink. - You should go.
-你又不用當班  -那就說定了
- You're not on duty. - That settles it, then.
等我沒事了來找你
I'll come find you when I'm released.
我們可以借輛車
We can borrow a car.
韋伯太太  我是這裡的女管家
Mrs. Webb, I am the housekeeper here.
只要國王陛下住在這裡
You are not housekeeper so long as
你就不是女管家
His Majesty is under this roof.
是  但他不是還沒來呢嗎
Yes, but he's not here yet, is he?
簡直像住在了工廠裡
It's like living in a factory.
讓我想起了戰時
It reminds me of our days
這裡做療養院的時候
as a convalescent home during the war.
我真喜歡那段時光
I enjoyed that,
但這麼說總讓我有些不好意思
although I always feel guilty saying so.
湯姆呢
Where's Tom?
-爸爸去村裡了  -又去了
- Daddy's in the village. - Again?
他幹什麼呢
What's he playing at?
我從車道走過來時  看到湯姆一臉嚴肅
I saw Tom looking very stern as I came up the drive.
希望他不是在造炸彈
I hope he's not building a bomb.
很多玩笑一語成讖呢
Many a true word is spoken in jest.
我們認為他被政治保安處盯梢了
We think he's being tailed by Special Branch.
怎麼可能
Nonsense.
-媽媽  倫敦如何  -還好
- Mama, how was London? - Oh, fine. Fine.
您去做什麼
What were you there for?
-就些事唄  -但您討厭倫敦
- Oh, various things. - But you hate London.
誰說的
Whoever told you that?
明天你要我什麼時候來
Now, when do you want me tomorrow?
最遲不超過12點
12:00 at the latest.
他們12:30到
They arrive at half past.
但媽媽  您可得保證不攻擊莫德•巴格肖
But, Mama, you must promise not to attack Maud Bagshaw.
我不能無視她
Well, I can't ignore her.
-她是我親戚呢  -就是啊
- She is my cousin. - Exactly.
像對親戚那樣打招呼  然後就別再多說了
Greet her as a cousin, and leave it at that.
我會考慮的
I'll think about it.
但即便她把財產都留給了外人  我們又能如何
But even if she has left everything to an outsider, what could we do?
挑戰遺囑
Challenge the will.
有什麼依據
On what basis?
不當影響
Undue influence.
您怎麼可能知道  又怎麼能證明
But how could you know that? And how would you prove it?
我們找個關係好的法官
We'd find a friendly judge.
關係好  還是腐敗
Friendly or corrupt?
只要能成功就行
Whichever does the trick.
您留下吃晚飯嗎  媽媽  是自助餐
Are you here for dinner, Mama? It's a buffet.
我沒換衣服
Well, I'm not changed.
我們也不換的
We won't change, either,
您摘了帽子就行
so you just need to take off your hat.
你怎麼說的那麼輕巧
You talk as if that were easy.
我的裁紙刀呢
Where's the paper knife,
銀的那把  有我軍團飾章的
the silver one with my regimental crest?
他們今晚不幫忙
They won't help tonight, apparently.
什麼都不做
They won't lift a finger.
不過話說回來  我做的飯只能給僕人吃嘛
But then, my food is only fit for servants.
至少你那位年輕英雄把熱水修好了
Well, at least your young hero seems to have sorted out the water.
他才不是我的英雄
He's not my hero.
是啊  你為什麼那麼說他
Yes. Why did you call him that?
就是開玩笑的
Oh, it was just a joke.
-哪裡好笑了  -安迪  行了
- But why's it funny? - Oh, Andy, leave it.
這就是個兔籠
But this is a rabbit hutch.
別看我  科貝特先生
Don't look at me, Mr. Courbet.
我的房間小的都丟不開貓
You couldn't swing a cat in my room.
先生們  行了  你們肯定會...
Gentlemen, please. I'm sure you'll find...
讓開
Out of my way.
我要洗個澡  然後再做決定
I will have a bath, and then I will decide.
或許我可以找家旅館
Perhaps I will find a hotel.
我們在哪吃飯  單獨的地方
Where can we eat? Somewhere apart?
去僕人休息室吃吧
Why not in the servants' hall?
我們從不跟本戶僕人一起吃
We never eat with the resident staff.
-借過  -水是冷的
- Excuse me. - The water's cold.
怎麼回事
What's happening?
真難以置信
Th-This is impossible.
沒有熱水我們不能住這裡
We can't stay here with no hot water.
-你瘋了嗎  -鍋爐今天才修好的
- Are you crazy? - But the boiler was fixed today.
一小時前還是熱的呢
It was hot an hour ago.
反正現在涼了
Well, it's cold now.
您是來幹什麼的來著  卡森先生
Why are you here again, Mr. Carson?
因為我控制不好局面  所以來頂替我嗎
So you could keep control when I would fail?
是這樣嗎  我忘了
Was that it? I-I forget.
你...巴羅先生  可以嗎
You... Mr. Barrow, would you mind?
當班的不是我  卡森先生  是你
I'm not on duty, Mr. Carson. You are.
抱歉  先生
Sorry, sir.
什麼事
What do you want?
因為你在我的房間  坐在我的桌前
Since you are in my room, sitting at my desk,
該我問你  你想要什麼
it is for me to ask what you want.
不需要你做什麼
Nothing from you.
我要提醒你
I would remind you
我可在唐頓主持事務很多年了
that I have been in charge of Downton for many years.
卡森先生  你是一棟地方小宅的
Mr. Carson, you are a retired servant
退休僕人
in a minor provincial house,
為一戶普通人家服務
serving an undistinguished family.
你的過往我絲毫不感興趣
Your history is of no interest to me.
失陪了
Now, if you will excuse me.
那你要我做什麼
So, what would you like me to do?
我要你找本好書
I would like you to find a good book
在我們走前  就好好看書
and read it until we leave.
卡森先生  您得來看看
Mr. Carson, you'd better come and see this.
壞的很徹底
It's well and truly damaged.
-你能及時修好嗎  -能
- Can you mend it in time? - Oh, yeah.
但得有人告訴他們
But somebody should tell them
有人想給皇室造訪搗亂
someone wanted to wreck the royal visit.
他們得知道
They ought to know.
-裙子到了嗎  -還沒呢
- Has the dress arrived? - Not yet.
-我要穿什麼啊  -卡森  怎麼了
- What am I going to wear? - Carson, what is it?
一些折疊椅
Some folding chairs...
是一大堆椅子被送來了  小姐
well, a great many chairs have been delivered, milady.
在後門呢
They're at the back door.
安娜覺得該馬上告訴您
Anna thought you should be told at once.
對  是給閱兵準備的
She's right. They're for the parade,
我們得今晚擺好
and we'll have to set them out tonight.
明天根本沒時間
There'll be no time tomorrow.
村民9點就會開始到了
The villagers will start arriving from 9:00 onwards.
命運可能並不垂青我們呢
I'm not sure fate is on our side.
可憐的小瑪麗
Poor little Mary.
我們是不是讓她承擔太多了
Have we let her take on too much?
是啊  走吧
Yes, you're right. Come on.
我們去幫幫她
We should lend her a hand.
這麼大的雨你不能出去
Well, you can't go out in this.
怎麼不能
Of course we can.
晚安  媽媽
Good night, Mama.
記得替我們祈禱  主要是祈禱天氣好轉
Remember to pray for us, mainly for better weather.
我會說句好話的
I'll put in a word.
不管  小瑪麗
Of course, little Mary could
能用牙釘帳篷樁呢
hammer in a tent peg with her teeth.
不知她這份狠勁是隨誰
I wonder who she got that from.
你讚美我時  我總感到驚訝
You know, I'm always surprised when you praise me.
你認為我讚美過你讓我驚訝
I'm surprised to hear that I have.
本來就狼狽  雷暴雨還來添亂
As if things aren't bad enough without a thunderstorm.
我們能行的  我叫來了莫斯利先生
We'll manage. I've roped in Mr. Molesley,
安迪去開貨車了
and Andy's gone for the truck.
但  貝茨先生幫不上忙
But, well, Mr. Bates can't help.
巴羅先生則不見人影
And Mr. Barrow has vanished.
我這邊也是  赫克瑟姆侯爵去找布蘭森先生了
Ditto. Lord Hexham's out looking for Mr. Branson.
我們只能自己盡力了
We'll have to do our best without them.
您不是要自己去吧
You're not going yourself?
不然誰指揮他們
Well, how else will they know what to do?
那我去拿大衣
Then I'll fetch our coats.
你不用來的
Well, you don't have to come.
我當然要來
Of course I do.
我去告訴貝茨先生我要去哪
I'll just tell Mr. Bates where I've gone.
你真是我的好朋友  安娜
You're a good friend to me, Anna.
我希望我們是彼此的好朋友  小姐
I hope we're good friends to each other, milady.
-應該就這些了  -好
- This should be the last of them. - Great.
那個給我  莫斯利先生
Okay, give me that, Mr. Molesley.
-能把繩子丟給我嗎  -給
- Can you chuck us the rope? - Here you go.
-系好了  系牢了  -我們來了
- Tie it down, make sure it's tight. - Here we are.
-都準備好了  -爸爸
- All set and ready. - Oh, Papa,
迪基  你們太好了  但真的沒事嗎
Dickie, you're so kind. But are you sure?
你們要濕透髒死的
You'll be soaked to the skin and filthy.
這對我們不算什麼  我們可是打獵的人
Well, what's that to us? We're hunting men.
-走吧  -你就不用來了  親愛的
- Come on. - You don't need to come, my dear.
交給我們就行
We can manage it between us.
我當然得去
Of course I'm coming.
走吧
Come along.
開心點  莫斯利
Cheer up, Molesley.
村民和來賓將從講臺兩邊觀禮
The villagers and guests will watch from both sides of the dais.
前面會給家裡人留座位
And there'll be seats at the front kept for the family.
-我跟你一起坐在那裡  -好吧
- I'll join you there. - I suppose so.
我們按說好的在主街碰面
We'll meet in the high street where we planned.
別帶別人來  自己來
Don't bring anyone. Come on your own.
真是荒唐
It's all ridiculous, of course.
就是小題大做
It's a lot of fuss over nothing.
什麼
What?
我以為你是來確保
I thought you were here to check
我不會做什麼蠢事鬧不愉快
I didn't do anything foolish and spoil things.
-怎麼說  -我不知道
- In what way? - I don't know.
丟雞蛋  揮橫幅  或喊話
Throw eggs or wave a banner or shout.
你會嗎
Will you?
不會
No.
但我開始懷疑你了
But I'm starting to wonder about you.
我不丟雞蛋
I don't throw eggs.
-再來嗎  -好
- Have another? - Yes.
-再來一樣的  謝謝  -好的  先生
- Same again, please. - Right you are, sir.
早餐過後我們再搬來
We'll bring a special chair up
專給王后準備的椅子
for the queen after breakfast
希望到時雨已經停了
when, hopefully, it will have stopped raining.
我親自搬  老爺
I shall carry it myself, milord.
-那國王呢  -他會騎馬的
- Well, what about the king? - Well, he'll be on his horse.
但如果還在下雨呢
But suppose it's still raining?
上帝會讓雨停的
God will make it stop.
那是湯姆嗎
Is that Tom?
他一晚上都在酒吧嗎
Has he been in the pub the whole evening?
天光大亮
Well, the day has dawned,
看這天氣  上帝絕對是君主主義者
and the weather proves conclusively that God is a monarchist.
誰都不會懷疑的  小姐
Who could doubt it, milady?
他們來了
Here they come now.
莫斯利先生
Mr. Molesley?
我沒事
I'm all right.
就是需要點時間喘勻氣
Just need a minute to catch my breath.
陛下
Your Majesties,
歡迎來到唐頓莊園
welcome to Downton Abbey.
我們很高興能來  格蘭瑟姆夫人
We're glad to be here, Lady Grantham.
格蘭瑟姆
Grantham.
您還記得格蘭瑟姆伯爵的母親吧
You remember Lord Grantham's mother.
你好  老格蘭瑟姆夫人
Hello, Lady Grantham.
需要我幫你嗎
Oh, can I help you?
我是需要幫助  先生  否則我要起不來了
Someone must, sir, or I... I may never rise again.
謝謝
Thank you.
我女兒  瑪麗•塔伯特夫人
My daughter, Lady Mary Talbot.
赫克瑟姆侯爵和夫人
The Marquess and Marchioness of Hexham.
湯姆•布蘭森先生
Mr. Tom Branson.
默頓伯爵和夫人
Lord and Lady Merton.
多謝你了
This is kind of you,
-格蘭瑟姆伯爵  -您太客氣了
- Lord Grantham. - Oh, not at all.
這是我們的殊榮
It is a great honor.
您肯定已經知道
I'm sure you know,
但瑪麗公主和拉塞爾斯伯爵
but Princess Mary and Lord Lascelles
會跟我們一起共進午餐  參觀閱兵
will be joining us for luncheon and the parade.
他們都來嗎
They're both coming?
據我所知是的
As far as I'm aware.
太好了
What a relief.
忘記我剛剛的話吧
Please forget I said that.
您說什麼了  陛下
Said what, ma'am?
-莫德堂親  -維奧蕾特
- Cousin Maud. - Violet.
我們不行親吻嗎
Are we going to kiss?
我很高興你還想親我
I'm glad you want to kiss me.
我上次收到你消息時  你可不是這個口風
It wasn't quite what you said when I last heard from you.
我寫信時也確實不想
Wasn't quite how I felt when I wrote.
需要我幫忙嗎
Can I help you at all?
謝謝  其他人都走了
Thanks. The others all shot off,
我不確定我是不是走對了
and I'm not sure if this is the right way.
跟我來吧
Just come with me.
你是做什麼的
What's your part in this circus?
我是巴格肖夫人的女僕
I'm Lady Bagshaw's maid.
那是這扇門了
Well, then it's this door.
你找休斯太太就好
You just ask for Mrs. Hughes.
-她會照顧你的  -謝謝
- She'll look after you. - Thank you.
你嘗過水了嗎
Oh, have you tasted the water?
只能洗漱  不能飲用
Only for body. Never for drinking.
這是寄給伊蒂絲小姐的
This has just arrived for Lady Edith.
是赫克瑟姆夫人了  貝茨先生  但...
Lady Hexham these days, Mr. Bates, but...
謝謝  亞伯特  真松了口氣
Thank you, Albert. It's a relief.
馬上給我牛奶
I want the milk now.
蛋黃
I want the egg yolks now.
橄欖油
I want the olive oil now.
還有香草莢
And I want the vanilla pod now.
他該馬上挨一耳光
He wants a clip around the ear... now.
注意點  派特莫太太
Careful, Mrs. Patmore.
好  誰端上去  莫斯利先生
Right. Who's taking this up? Mr. Molesley?
您不必插手  休斯太太
There's no need for you to meddle, Mrs. Hughes.
-我們會處理的  -插手
- We will see to it. - Meddle?
我在自己家裡可不算"插手"  謝謝
I don't believe I'm meddling in my own house, thank you.
安德魯  對
Andrew, yes.
-你把那個端上去  -但這不是你家  是吧
- You take that one. - But it's not your house, is it?
你要不要去坐下
So, would you like to go and sit down?
-你給我等等  -你別管了
- Now, just a minute. - Uh, you leave those.
放下
Put them down.
老天  去追他們
For heaven's sake, go after them.
我得提出抗議  我的手下...
I really must protest. My staff are...
讓他們待在這下面  卡森先生
Keep them down here, Mr. Carson.
你也是
That goes for you, too.
別礙我的事
Stay out of our way.
你們已經見到陛下了  知足吧
You've seen Their Majesties. Let it be enough.
-幹什麼  -等等
- Excuse me. - Wait a minute.
你們在幹什麼
What-what are you playing at?
等等
Hang on.
什麼...
What...?
北部的情況似乎平靜了一些
Things seem calmer in the north.
您是指罷工的事嗎  先生
You mean after the strike, sir?
是啊  如果平靜是順從的意思
Yes, if calmer means more resigned.
我不確定未來會如何
I'm not sure what the future holds.
您呢  格蘭瑟姆老夫人
And you, Lady Grantham.
您受到大罷工的影響了嗎
Were you affected by the general strike?
罷工期間  我的女僕對我挺粗魯的  先生
Well, my maid was rather curt with me while it was on, sir.
但她心底裡是個共產主義者
But, you know, she is a communist at heart.
所以大概也不奇怪
So I suppose it was only to be expected.
公主不來嗎
Wasn't the princess joining us?
他們來了電話
They telephoned.
拉塞爾斯伯爵被什麼事耽擱了
Lord Lacelles has been held up by something.
但他們是打算來參加閱兵的
but they are planning to come for the parade.
這裡的僕人臥室不錯吧
I imagine the servants' bedrooms are quite pleasant here.
怎麼  您擔心您的女僕嗎
Why? Are you worried for your maid?
你真聰明
How clever of you.
比起女僕  露西更多是位伴侶
Lucy is more of a companion than a maid.
我不希望她不舒服
I'd hate for her to be uncomfortable.
當然了
Of course.
我真的得走了
I really have to go.
你不能讓媽媽難堪
You can't embarrass Mama.
抱歉  但你得等到我們離席
I'm sorry, but you must wait until we stand.
赫克瑟姆侯爵  諾森伯蘭郡如何了
Lord Hexham, how is Northumberland?
還是一如既往的美麗  先生
As beautiful as ever, sir.
你離開那裡能行嗎
Can it spare you, do you think?
真是羞辱人
Well, that was humiliating.
走吧
Go on.
我們都去散步得了
Well, we might as well all go for a walk.
我們不能改變
We cannot challenge the way
皇室造訪的一貫規矩  派特莫太太
a royal visit is conducted, Mrs. Patmore.
那可未必
I'm not so sure.
閱兵結束後  我們回這裡見吧
Why don't we all meet back here after the parade?
安娜  貝茨先生
Anna, Mr. Bates,
絕不能有任何麻煩  或不忠的愚蠢行為
there must be no trouble or disloyal tomfoolery of any kind.
聽到了嗎
Do you hear me?
我們去酒窖見
We'll meet in the wine cellar.
轉告其他人
Tell the others.
我要去貝克韋爾先生那裡
Now, I'm walking to Mr. Bakewell's,
-你有事要我代辦嗎  -沒有
- if you've any errands. -  No.
那麼
Well, then,
-我們該走了  -好的  先生
- we should get moving. - Of course, sir.
-好  -走咯
- Yes. - Here we go.
-陛下  -我好期待
- Ma'am. - I'm so looking forward to this.
-好  -這頓午飯還不錯
- Okay. - Good lunch, I thought.
國王之前說了什麼  我沒聽清
What was the king saying earlier? I couldn't hear.
他計畫明年3月安排威爾士王子出行
He's planning a tour for the Prince of Wales next March.
要把大部分非洲殖民地走一遍
It'll take in most of the African colonies
-最後到開普敦  -他要你去嗎
- and finish in Cape Town. - And he wants you to go?
他覺得我能穩住他
He thinks I'm a steadying influence.
你要走多久
How long would you be away?
大概三個月
About three months.
我真是太走運了  你說呢
I can't believe my luck. Can you?
車好像停在了後面
I think we're parked around the back.
湯姆
Tom.
你在這裡做什麼
What on earth are you doing here?
我還想問你呢
I might ask you the same question.
快回去  不然你會壞事的
Go back, or you'll ruin things.
你不是就想壞事嗎
Isn't that what you're doing?
你什麼都不知道
You don't know what I'm doing.
-這是誰  -我的大姨子
- Who's this? - This is my sister-in-law,
瑪麗•塔伯特夫人
Lady Mary Talbot.
我叫你一個人來的
I told you to come alone.
交給我吧
Leave this to me.
-湯姆  -拿槍
- Tom! - Get the gun!
他在這兒
There he is.
-別動  -抓住了嗎
- Hold still. - Got him?
冷靜下來  你別想跑了
Calm down. You're not going anywhere.
-別動  -你沒事吧  先生
- Hold still. - Are you all right, sir?
-叛國罪  -夫人
- High treason, that is. - Your Ladyship?
你們怎麼跑來的
Why are you even here?
我也是到昨晚才懷疑起了他
I didn't suspect him myself until last night.
我怎麼會知道你放棄了愛爾蘭的自由
How was I to know you'd given up on a free Ireland?
它現在不自由嗎
Isn't it free now?
被王權踩著脖子叫什麼自由
Not with the bloody Crown around its neck!
上車
Get in.
-帶他走  -好  先生
- Take him away. - All right, sir.
我可不喜歡你們都認定了
I'm not impressed you all decided
我企圖行刺皇室
I was a royal assassin.
我沒啊
I didn't.
是其他人這麼想
It was really the others.
請您跟我們去趟警局
If you'll follow us to the station.
你怎麼沒告訴我們
Why didn't you tell us?
我原以為他是來查我的
I thought he'd come to check up on me
就不想把你們捲進來
and didn't want to drag you into it.
我以為我跟他喝杯酒
I assumed he'd back off
好好回答他的問題  他就會放過我
if I answered his questions and met him for a drink.
但昨晚在酒吧
But last night at the pub,
我意識到他是想利用我接近國王
I realized he wanted to use me to get close to the king.
皇室敬禮
Royal salute!
執劍
Carry... swords!
抱歉
Sorry.
不好意思
Excuse me.
我們以為你們不來了
We thought you'd miss it.
這不正趕上了
I was just in time.
真不知我何必來
I don't know why I bothered.
別說話
Oh, quiet.
陛下
Your Majesty,
約克郡輕騎兵已列隊完畢
the Yorkshire Hussars are formed up, ready
等待您的檢閱
and awaiting your inspection.
他人呢
Where is he?
他不太舒服
He's not feeling well.
他昨天不還去打獵了嗎
Wasn't he out shooting yesterday?
-您要我說什麼  -什麼都不用說
- What do you want me to say? - Nothing.
您得允許我離開他
You have to let me leave him.
我們現在不談這個
We will not talk about it now.
那是你的女僕嗎
Is that your maid?
沒錯  露西
That's right. Lucy.
你不稱呼她的姓氏嗎
Don't you call her by her surname?
她跟我很久了
She's been with me so long.
警局
好奇怪
It's so strange.
-他看上去很像英格蘭人  -他以前是的
- He seemed so English. - And so he was.
曾是政府人員
A pillar of the establishment,
但愛爾蘭獨立的念頭
until the notion of Irish independence
讓他站到了另一邊
took him over to the other side.
於是打起了我的主意
That's where I came in.
他聽說我心裡向著愛爾蘭和共和黨
He'd heard my sympathies lay with Ireland and the republic.
難道不是嗎
Don't they?
也不是不顧一切的
Not at any cost.
我現在是個顧及法律秩序的人
I'm a law-and-order man these days.
那是你們對我的改造
That's what you lot have done to me.
這事會在報紙上
So, will there be a great splash
被大肆報導嗎
all over the newspapers?
可憐的爸爸
Poor Papa.
不  你會發現此事完全不會傳開
Oh, no. You'll find there isn't a whisper about this anywhere.
政府掩蓋
An establishment cover-up.
我不相信陰謀論
I don't believe in conspiracy theories.
是啊
Yes.
-你寫作嗎  -儘量吧
- Do you... do you write? - I try.
史密斯小姐  休斯太太給你安排好了吧
Miss Smith. Did Mrs. Hughes sort you out?
是的
She did.
你喜歡閱兵嗎
And have you enjoyed the parade?
你在家裡幹活兒嗎
Do you work at the house?
不是的
Not exactly.
我賣車  並幫忙打理地產
I sell cars, and I help with the estate.
格蘭瑟姆伯爵是我的岳父
Lord Grantham is my father-in-law.
真抱歉了  先生
Oh, I do beg your pardon, sir.
沒事  容我解釋
Oh, no, please, let me explain.
我起初是這裡的司機
I started here as a chauffeur.
你就是茜玻小姐的丈夫吧
You must be Lady Sybil's husband.
是的
I am.
巴格肖夫人和我知道你們的事
Lady Bagshaw and I followed the story.
她死時我們好難過
We were so sad when she died.
那是多久以前了
How long ago was it?
快七年了
Seven years, or nearly.
-天啊  -真抱歉
- My God. - I'm sorry.
-還很心痛吧  -也不算
- It's still painful. - Not in that way.
雖然不心痛了  但還在心裡
It doesn't hurt anymore, but it's still there.
-可以問你件事嗎  -當然
- Can I ask you something? - Of course.
你覺得難嗎  改變地位
Was it hard, coming up like that?
成為這家的人
Joining the family.
是很難
Very hard.
夾在我的舊世界和新世界之間
Between my old world and the new one,
有時讓我搞不清自己的身份
sometimes I didn't know who I was.
但你現在知道了
But you do now?
我覺得是的
I think so, yes.
我已經接受了
I came to terms with it.
怎麼了
Why?
我就是好奇
I'm just curious.
大家快點
Quickly, everyone. Quick.
快來  巴羅先生
Come on. Quickly, Mr. Barrow.
誰告訴我到底怎麼回事  安娜
Can somebody tell me what's going on? Anna?
怎麼回事
What's going on?
我們在這下面幹什麼
What are we all doing down here?
進去  在那裡他們聽不到
Go inside. They can't hear us in there.
這太不成體統了
This is most improper.
你叫我們來這裡幹什麼
Yes, why-why have you got us all here?
-是啊  -聽我說
- Yeah. - I will tell you.
貝茨先生和我
Mr. Bates and I...
我們想維護唐頓的尊嚴
we want to defend Downton's honor.
怎麼說
In what way?
你們想再次遭受午餐時的對待嗎
Would you like a repeat of how you were all treated at luncheon?
不  我當然不想
No, I bloody well would not.
安德魯  當著女士怎麼說話呢
Andrew, there are ladies present.
我們覺得我們該反抗
We think we should fight back.
我不喜歡這口氣
I don't like the sound of this.
我完全不喜歡
I do not like this at all.
安娜  說吧
Anna, tell them.
我們要掃清障礙  讓你們能夠
We are going to clear the way so you cook and serve dinner
在唐頓莊園為國王和王后做飯  服侍他們
for the king and queen at Downton Abbey.
這也是本該的
As you should.
天啊  這是革命嗎
Well, oh, my God, is this a revolution?
要我去拿乾草叉嗎
Shall I fetch the pitchforks?
我們說真的  莫斯利先生
No, we're serious, Mr. Moseley.
但你知道科貝特先生今晚拿了什麼來嗎
But do you know what Mr. Courbet's brought in for tonight?
別管那個了  我們自有原料
Mm, never mind that. We've got our own supplies.
科貝特先生就交給我吧
And you can leave Mr. Courbet to me.
你要我們做什麼
What do you want us to do?
別管那些女僕和貼身男僕
Don't bother with the maids and valets.
我們跟他們沒仇沒怨
We've no quarrel with them.
但我們今晚得支開皇室管家
But we need to get rid of the royal butler for the night.
是侍從長
The Page of the Backstairs,
別說錯了  貝茨先生
if you don't mind, Mr. Bates.
男僕也得被支開
And the footmen need to be out of commission
從7點到你們結束侍餐
from 7:00 until you finish serving them.
這是叛國
This is treason.
我們怎麼支開他們
Well, what can we do about 'em?
我們可以把他們鎖在閣樓裡
Well, we could lock them in the attic.
再說這種話
Any more talk like that,
我們都要被流放了
and we'll all end up in Botany Bay.
難道你喜歡
And did you enjoy
被威爾森先生欺負
being pushed around and passed over
忽視  被他呵斥待在樓下嗎
and told to stay down here by Mr. Wilson?
我絕不要主動參與此事
I will play no active part in this.
萬一被陛下發現了
Well, suppose His Majesty sees
我們的小動作  惹他不高興了呢
what's going on and is displeased.
怎麼  你覺得我做不好一頓體面的晚宴嗎
Why? Do you think I'm not capable of cooking a decent dinner?
當然不是  但是...
Oh, no, of course not. But-but I...
男僕交給我
I'll see to the footmen.
你打算做什麼
What are you going to do?
等著瞧吧
You'll find out.
那我們又恢復工作了嗎
So, does this mean we're back on duty after all?
-我和莫斯利先生  -還有亞伯特
- Me and Mr. Moseley? - And Albert as well.
你們知道高級號服在哪
You know where to find the state liveries.
好
Right.
-走吧  黛西  -我能為
- Well, come on, Daisy. - Will I pour wine
王后的朱唇倒酒嗎
for the queen's sweet lips?
再犯傻  我們就把你鎖在閣樓裡
Any more of that, and we'll lock you in the attic.
真不知你何必這麼激動
I don't know why you're bothering.
那個韋伯太太呢
What about that Mrs. Webb
總說她才是女管家
who keeps telling us she's the housekeeper?
你別擔心韋伯太太了
Don't you worry about Mrs. Webb.
她才不是我的對手
I am more than a match for Mrs. Webb.
我還是不知道你打算怎麼對付科貝特先生
I still don't know how you're going to manage Mr. Courbet.
這個嘛...
Well, there's, um...
我要去樓上躺會兒
I'm just going upstairs to lie down.
我回來時  你能把一切準備好吧
Can you get things ready for when I come back?
你什麼時候回來  大老爺
When will that be, O Mighty One?
半小時後
Wake me in half an hour
如果我還沒下來  去叫我
if I'm not already in the kitchen.
相信我們吧
Trust us.
跟我們說說你的女僕
Tell us about your maid.
露西的父親
Lucy is the daughter of...
是大衛軍隊的僕人  傑克•史密斯的女兒
David's army servant, Jack Smith.
他跟我丈夫都死在了布林戰爭戰場
And, like my husband, he died in the Boer Wars.
於是你就照顧起了他的孩子
So you looked after his child?
露西沒有媽媽
Lucy had no mother, you see.
我就給了她個家
So I gave her a home.
真是好心
That's very generous.
相信我  這份好心得到了她盡心報答了
Generosity that has been amply returned, I can assure you.
那太好了
I'm glad.
聽上去言不由衷啊
You don't sound very glad.
天啊
Oh, goodness.
我以為大家都在客廳裡
I thought everyone was in the drawing room.
恐怕我在回避他們呢
I've been dodging it, I'm afraid.
我想我該回去了
I suppose I ought to get back.
需要我替你叫誰來嗎
Can I get someone for you?
不用了  謝謝
No, thank you.
你是這家小女兒的鰥夫  對吧
You're the widower of the youngest daughter, aren't you?
我聽說過你  你叫...
I've heard of you, Mister...
布蘭森
Branson.
湯姆•布蘭森
Tom Branson.
你是哪位
And who are you?
我該知道的
Ah, I should know,
但我不擅長這種事
but I'm no good at that sort of thing.
你也不可能認得每一個人
Well, I suppose you can't be expected to know everyone.
你覺得閱兵精彩嗎
Did you enjoy the parade?
恐怕我完全錯過了
I'm afraid I missed it completely.
我另有事要辦
I got distracted.
-真可惜  -說實話
- What a shame. - Well, to be honest,
我不算是保皇黨
I'm not much of a royalist.
雖然我不應該大聲說出來
Although I probably shouldn't say that out loud.
更不應該對陌生人說
Certainly not to a stranger.
這好奇怪  因為如有必要
That seems odd, as the Crawleys
卡勞利家的人願為國王獻出生命
would die for the Crown if they had to.
你可以愛跟你有分歧的人
You can love people you disagree with.
你愛他們嗎
And you love them?
他們本質很正派
They're decent at the core.
有些人本質正派  但很難一起生活
People can be decent at the core but very difficult to live with.
說得很對
True enough.
他們有時也會犯傻  勢利
And they're silly, too, and snobbish at times.
我一點也不贊同他們的政見
And I wouldn't give tuppence for their politics.
但我已經能欣然接受那一切了
But I've learned to be happy with all of that.
再說
And besides...
他們是我女兒的家人
they're my daughter's family.
她住在這兒嗎
And she lives here?
有一次我差點帶她走了
I nearly took her away once.
但她現在屬於這裡
But she belongs here now.
我人生曾有很長一段時間不屬於任何地方
I spent so much of my life not belonging anywhere.
那對我來說很重要
That's important to me.
我想歸根結底
I suppose, in the end,
還是得決定什麼才是最重要的  對嗎
it's deciding what's important, isn't it?
你給了我很多值得思考的事  布蘭森先生
You've given me a great deal to think about, Mr. Branson.
希望是好事
Good things, I hope.
也許吧  但是
That may be so, but...
現在我們必須進去了
now we must go in.
我們得換衣服
We must change.
而且你明早就出發
And you leave in the morning.
我們晚點能談談嗎
I wonder if we might have a talk later.
找個舒適的地方
We'll find a cozy spot.
羅伯特也來加入我們
And Robert can join us.
我不想被盤問  維奧萊特
I won't be interrogated, Violet.
請別錯過解決你們矛盾的機會
Please, don't miss the chance to settle things between you.
好吧
Very well.
但現在我得走了
But now I must go.
你幫了我  謝謝你
That was helpful. Thank you.
我跟你說了我想幫忙
Well, I told you I wanted to help.
多虧了你  她這下無處可逃了
Well, thanks to you, we have her cornered.
威爾森先生
Mr. Wilson.
有人打電話找你
There's a telephone call for you.
找我
For me?
但是  哈裡爵士  他們9點才能到倫敦
But, Sir Harry, they wouldn't get to London until 9:00.
這沒關係
It doesn't matter.
克拉倫斯府的舞會10點才開始
The ball at Clarence House won't start till 10:00.
克拉倫斯府的什麼舞會
What ball at Clarence House?
康諾特公爵辦的
The Duke of Connaught's.
你到底在搞什麼名堂  威爾森
What are you playing at, Wilson?
我不是在質疑您  先生
I'm not questioning you, sir,
既然這是康諾特公爵的意思
not if it's what the Duke of Connaught wishes.
但我這裡該怎麼辦
But how do I manage here?
唐頓莊園沒有男僕嗎
Don't they have footmen at Downton?
有男僕  但國王陛下不會...
Yes, there are footmen. But won't His Majesty...
國王陛下才不在乎
His Majesty won't give a tinker's cuss!
照我說的做
Now, do as I say.
好  哈裡爵士  我馬上去辦
Of course, Sir Harry. At once.
沒出什麼事吧  威爾森先生
Everything all right, Mr. Wilson?
我需要見我的男僕
I need to see my footmen
莊園的男僕  以及門童
and the house footmen and the hall boy.
下一班去倫敦的火車是何時
when is the next train to London?
希望不是壞消息
I hope it's not bad news.
算不上壞
Not bad, exactly.
但不合常規
But irregular.
非常不合常規
Very irregular, indeed.
如果他們發現了  會把我趕走的
I'll get drummed out of the regiment if they ever find out.
反正我覺得你聽起來毫無破綻
Well, you sounded convincing to me.
我很擅長模仿哈裡•巴恩斯頓爵士
Oh, I'm very good at doing Sir Harry Barnston,
我可以向你保證
I can assure you.
如果威爾森先生打回去怎麼辦
What if Mr. Wilson rings back?
沒人敢質疑哈裡爵士的命令
No one queries Sir Harry's orders.
但萬一他打了呢
But if he did?
那他們就會發現這是騙局
Well, then they'd uncover the trick.
但他們不會知道是我幹的
But they couldn't trace it back to me.
好了  我們去約克吧
Right. Shall we go into York?
錯失樂趣  有點遺憾呢
Sorry to miss out on the fun, in a way.
你和父母見面時  我該在哪等你
Where shall I wait for you when you're with your parents?
我們找家酒館
We'll find a pub.
你聯繫到人了嗎
Did you manage to speak to someone?
我聯繫上了西摩女士的助手
I got hold of Madame Seymour's assistant.
他們寄錯了裙子
They've sent you the wrong one.
款式類似  但是  如您所見  尺寸不同
It's similar in style but not, as you can see, in size.
那我的裙子現在在哪
Well, where's my dress now?
在去紐約的路上
On its way to New York.
那就沒辦法了
Well, that's that, then.
太好了
Wonderful.
我今天事事不順
Everything's going wrong for me today.
-小姐  -不說了
- Milady? - Oh. Never mind.
樓下的情況怎麼樣  好點了嗎
How are things downstairs? Any better?
好點了  小姐
A bit better, yes, milady.
事實上  我該回去了
In fact, I ought to be getting back.
去吧
Of course.
有件事
Oh, one thing.
我床前以前放的彩色玻璃杯
The painted glass that used to sit by my bed,
是我不在時打壞了嗎
was it broken while I was away?
交給我吧  小姐
Leave it with me, milady.
裙子也交給我吧
And the dress.
你今晚稍後可以試衣嗎
You wouldn't mind a fitting later tonight, would you?
我不明白  跟誰試衣
I don't understand. Who with?
我剛想了個主意
I just had an idea.
我看不會
I shouldn't think so,
如果她還知道好歹的話
not if she knows what's good for her.
我...
Oh, I...
抱歉打擾
I'm sorry to interrupt.
你找到我了  真是機智
How clever of you to find me.
算不上  我在這裡住了40年呢
Well, not really. I lived here 40 years.
這是你的女僕吧
I assume this is your maid?
對  這是露西•史密斯
Yes, this is Lucy Smith.
晚上好  史密斯
Good evening, Smith.
晚上好  夫人
Good evening, milady.
-那我下去了  -不必為我離開
- Shall I go? - No, not for me. Not for me.
我很高興能見到你
I'm delighted to meet you.
我聽說了你好多事呢
I've heard so much about you.
你有什麼事嗎
Is there something you want?
就是確保你一切妥當
Oh, just-just to see you're comfortable
並確認下我們稍後的聊天
and to confirm our little chat for later.
我現在的生活自己做主了  維奧蕾特
I live my own life now, Violet.
我不像以前了
I'm not what I was.
我父親死了  我丈夫死了
My father is gone. My husband is gone.
我已經沒理由不按自己的意思生活了
I see no reason not to do what I want.
不是沒有理由
Well, that doesn't mean there is no reason,
只是你看不到
merely that you cannot see it.
我覺得默頓夫人說得對
I think Lady Merton is right.
我們應該徹底解決此事
We'll have it out, once and for all.
但現在  我得去侍奉陛下了
But now I must go to Her Majesty.
你們不能說話  不能思考
You're not to speak. You're not to think.
只管聽我命令
Just follow my lead.
絕不能讓陛下發現  僕人換了
Their Majesties must not know they're being served by anyone different.
聽到了嗎
Do you hear me?
我甚至不希望他們有所察覺
I don't want them to even notice.
我們會盡力的  威爾森先生
We will do our best, Mr. Wilson.
盡力可不夠
I don't want your best.
要比盡力還好很多
I want far better than your best.
這裡一切都好嗎  威爾森先生
Is everything under control here, Mr. Wilson?
聽說其他人已上了車
I gather the others caught the train.
我們只剩他們了
And this is what we're left with.
可不要給高級號服抹黑  亞伯特
Mind you don't disgrace the state livery, Albert.
當然  卡森先生
Of course, Mr. Carson.
科貝特先生呢
Where is Monsieur Courbet?
-我是來找他的  -他出去了
- I came in here to see him. - Uh, he went out.
所以我想著  我最好趕緊把飯做好
So I thought I'd better get on with dinner.
我說的是吧
Wasn't I right?
不  你說的不是  大錯特錯
No, you were not right. You were entirely wrong!
對不起
Oh, I'm sorry.
我也不知道怎麼會這樣
I don't know h-how that happened.
我得去換衣服
Well, I shall have to go and change.
等我回來  再解決此事
We'll sort this out when I return.
安迪
Andy.
如果你不希望我去  我就不去
If you don't want me to, I won't.
但你都答應了
But you've already said that you will.
因為這機會難得
Because it's a fantastic chance.
我沒想到你會介意
It didn't occur to me you'd mind.
我並不是介意  不是那樣
I don't, exactly. Not in that way.
那是怎樣
Then in what way?
我本沒想告訴你的
I wasn't going to tell you.
我本沒想告訴任何人的  但是
I wasn't going to tell anyone, but...
我可能懷孕了
I might be pregnant.
親愛的
Oh, darling.
太棒了
How marvelous.
太好了
How fabulous.
我的心要跳出來了
My heart is bursting.
所以我才不想說
Oh, well, that's exactly what I don't want.
-很可能會出岔子的  -但如果一切順利
- It could easily go wrong. - Oh, but-but if it doesn't...
那我生孩子時
Then I'll give birth
你剛好要去殖民地巡視三個月
just as you set off on your three-month colonial tour.
我剛說時你怎麼不提
Why didn't you say this when I first mentioned it?
我沒來得及說你就答應了
You'd agreed before I had the chance.
秘密總會壞事
Secrets always muddle things.
是啊  對  說成是我的錯吧
Oh, yes, that's right, let's make it my fault.
那我告訴國王我去不了了
Well, I'll tell the king I can't go.
他能接受嗎
And he'll accept that, will he?
你好  是史密斯小姐  是吧
Hello. It's Miss Smith, isn't it?
我們之前還在聊你呢  是吧
We were talking about you earlier. Weren't we?
湯姆
Oh, Tom.
太好了  你認識史密斯小姐吧
What luck. You know Miss Smith, don't you?
來吧  瑪麗
Come along, Mary.
你沒事吧
Are you all right?
出什麼事了嗎
Has something happened?
我們更衣時  格蘭瑟姆老夫人進來了
Old Lady Grantham came in while we were dressing.
我覺得她們稍後要大吵一架了  為了我
I think the stage is set for a fight later, about me.
她認為巴格肖夫人有意照顧我
She thinks Lady Bagshaw means to favor me,
-而她不贊成  -這與她何干
- and she doesn't approve. - What business is it of hers?
巴格肖夫人肯定自有原因
Lady Bagshaw must have her reasons,
這對我就夠了
and that's good enough for me.
下去嗎  湯姆
Going down, Tom?
再見
Good night.
你在這裡呢  勞頓小姐
There you are, Miss Lawton.
希望你還舒服  你也該好好休息了
I hope you're having a well-earned rest.
阿普林小姐一來  我就沒什麼可做的了
Well, there's always less for me to do when Miss Aplin arrives.
但我們還得為明天的舞會做好準備
But we must be ready for the ball tomorrow.
我就想找你說這事
That's what I want to talk about.
今晚晚些時候  等我去服侍赫克瑟姆夫人時
Later this evening, when I go up to help Lady Hexham,
我希望你也來
I want you to come with me,
為她的新舞會裙改尺寸  連夜修好
fit a new ball dress and sew it overnight
你明早走前弄妥當
so it's done before you leave in the morning.
我為什麼要那麼做
Why on earth would I do that?
客廳的盒子和丘比特
The box and cupid from the drawing room.
圖書館的裁紙刀
The library paper knife.
還有赫克瑟姆夫人的彩色玻璃杯
Lady Hexham's painted glass.
玻璃杯不是我拿的
Never took the glass.
那肯定是像她說的  是打壞了
Then it must have been broken, like she said.
但你也拿了那個房間的東西
But you took something from that room.
是什麼
What was it?
梳粧檯的堵漏盒
A patch box from the dressing table.
請都還回來
I'd like them all back, please.
我沒法一夜改好裙子
I can't sew a dress in a night.
我還睡不睡了
When would I sleep?
明天到了哈伍德再睡吧
When you get to Harewood tomorrow.
別以為我不會說出去
And don't think I won't tell.
"王后的服裝師是個小偷"
"Queen's dresser a thief."
從這裡到秘魯的報紙都會頭條報導
That'll make headlines from here to Peru.
格蘭比侯爵和侯爵夫人
The Marquess and Marchioness of Granby.
威廉爵士和英格比夫人
Sir William and Lady Ingleby.
皇家男僕都哪去了
Where are the royal footmen?
他們不得不回倫敦了
They've had to go back to London.
都回去了嗎  太不巧了吧
All of them? Wasn't that rather unlucky?
對於某些人來說是吧  小姐
Unlucky for some, milady.
斯卡伯勒伯爵和伯爵夫人
The Earl and Countess of Scarborough.
天啊
For goodness' sake!
幫幫我
Help me!
誰來幫幫我
Will someone help me?
我待會兒去特頓酒吧
I'm going on to Turton's in a minute.
你知道那裡嗎
Do you know it?
我是克裡斯•韋伯斯特
I'm Chris Webster, by the way.
我在等人
I'm waiting for someone.
等好久了
For a very long time.
或許他找到更有意思的事做了
Perhaps he's found better things to do.
怎麼
And?
你跟我來吧
Why don't you come with me?
你知道你想的
You know you want to.
不好意思  先生  我叫巴羅
Excuse me, sir. My name's Barrow.
如果有人來找我  就告訴他我走了
If someone comes looking for me, could you tell him I've gone?
我該說你去哪了呢
Shall I say where to?
-別管了  -特頓酒吧
- Never mind that. - Turton's.
我不明白威爾森先生是去哪了
I just cannot understand where Mr. Wilson has got to.
管他呢  你怎麼辦
Never mind him. What about you?
你不會真要讓陛下沒人服侍吧
Surely, you can't really mean to leave His Majesty unattended.
但由我服侍他妥當嗎
But is it for me to attend him?
你都穿戴好了嘛
Well, you've got your breeches on.
-這倒是  但...  -卡森先生
- Well, I have, but... - Mr. Carson,
這是你的宿命
this is your destiny.
你跟我一樣清楚
You know as much, and so do I.
驕傲地接受吧
Now, accept it proudly.
抬起頭  走進那個房間
And walk into that room with your head held high.
您可以的  卡森先生
You can do it, Mr. Carson.
請告訴我到底是怎麼回事
Please tell me what is going on.
科貝特先生不見了  威爾森先生也是
Mr. Courbet is missing, ditto Mr. Wilson,
您的男僕  在去倫敦的路上
and your footmen are on their way up to London.
我還是負責人
I am still in charge here.
不  韋伯太太  他們可是我的人
No, Mrs. Webb. These are my people now.
所以拜託你回僕人休息室坐下吧
So please, uh, go back to the servants' hall and sit down.
難道你要讓今晚鬧得不愉快嗎
Or would you rather ruin the evening?
叫她知道厲害了
That's telling her.
派特莫太太忘記送醬汁上去了
Mrs. Patmore forgot to send up the sauce.
我拿了碎雞蛋
And I've got the chopped egg.
多謝你了  這不是你的職責
Oh, that's kind when it's not your job.
說什麼呢
Nonsense.
我們今晚可都得為唐頓的榮譽出力
We must all pull our weight tonight for Downton's glory.
準備好了嗎  孩子們
Now, are you ready, boys?
不會準備得更好了
Ready as we'll ever be.
我們沒事的  休斯太太
We'll be fine, Mrs. Hughes.
你呢  莫斯利先生
What about you, Mr. Molesley?
我肯定會忘詞的
I know I'm gonna forget my lines.
你沒詞啊
You haven't got any lines.
-你該上了  -好
- You're on. - Right.
莫斯利先生
And, Mr. Molesley?
記得呼吸
Remember to breathe.
呼吸  好
Breathe, yeah.
先生們
Gentlemen.
很高興有你在  卡森先生
I'm glad you're here, Mr. Carson.
國王需要我  我責無旁貸
I must go where my king needs me.
-你好  -好
- Hello. - All right.
你好
Oh, hello.
看來來了新血呢
Looks like we've got some new blood here.
你好
Hello.
你真是個帥小夥
You're a very charming young man.
留下嘛  留下吧  邁克爾
Stay with me! Stay with me, Michael!
難以置信
I can't believe this.
我從未見過這樣的地方
I've never seen anything like it.
凡事都有第一次
There's a first time for everything.
我知道  但...
I know, but...
來  跟我跳舞
Here. Come dance with me.
-你說什麼  -我說"你朋友在那兒"
- What'd you say? - I said, "There's your friend."
不  我朋友在那兒
No, my friend's over there.
我真希望我能告訴他們  他們該多感激你
I wish I could tell them how grateful they should be to you.
你跟我一樣勇敢的
You were every bit as brave as I was.
瑪麗
Mary,
你該跟另一邊聊天
you're talking in the wrong direction.
別擔心奶奶
Don't worry about Granny.
她在準備拷問莫德堂親呢
She's getting ready to give Cousin Maud a grilling.
我猜主要是為了她女僕的事
Mainly, I suspect, about her maid.
我覺得巴格肖夫人並不只把她當做女僕
I think Lady Bagshaw sees her as more than just her maid.
肯定的
Oh, I'm sure she does.
這正是奶奶害怕的
And that's what Granny's afraid of.
我不妨承認
I might as well admit...
我喜歡她
I like her.
很好
Good.
別讓他們嚇退你
Don't let them put you off.
湯姆  你好像很高興
Tom, you're looking pleased with yourself.
他只是在讚揚巴格肖夫人的女僕
He was just praising Lady Bagshaw's maid.
她是怎麼使手腕攀上你的
Well, uh, how did she contrive to make your acquaintance?
她沒使手腕  我們碰巧遇到的
She didn't contrive anything. We met by chance.
男人可真蠢
What simpletons men are.
這真不錯
This is good.
但我以為定好的菜單是別的
And I thought something else was planned.
但真是美味
But it is excellent.
老科貝特做得不錯
So, a well-done to old Courbet.
-是啊  -真好吃
- Oh, yes. - Yes, very delicious.
這可不是科貝特先生做的  陛下
This wasn't Monsieur Courbet, Your Majesty.
是派特莫太太做的
Mrs. Patmore cooked it.
事實上  今晚為您服務的
In fact, it is the Downton Abbey staff
是唐頓莊園的僕人
who are serving you this evening.
抱歉  陛下
I do beg your pardon, Your Majesty.
行了  莫斯利
That's quite enough, Molesley.
你可要代我們向派特莫太太和全體僕人
You must give our compliments to Mrs. Patmore
表示感激
and all the staff.
莫斯利
Molesley.
王后陛下在跟你說話呢
Her Majesty is speaking to you.
當然  陛下
With pleasure, Your Majesty.
您真是客氣了  陛下
That was kind of you, ma'am.
能接過我們帶來的僕人的工作
I suppose he's excited that they've had to take over
他肯定頗為激動
from our people.
不知是發生了什麼
I wonder what's happened.
不管發生了什麼  他都太不得體了
Whatever may have happened does not excuse his behavior.
相信我  格蘭瑟姆夫人
I can assure you, Lady Grantham,
我們習慣了人們在我們面前
we are quite used to people behaving strangely
表現失常
when we are near.
沒事  有我呢
That's it. I've got you.
員警來了
The peelers are here!
是員警
It's the police!
別讓他們跑了  堵住所有出口
Make sure no one scarpers. Block all the exits.
-怎麼回事  -好了  先生們
- What's going on? - All right, gentlemen,
今晚的娛樂結束了  把音樂關了
that's the end of your evening. Shut that music up now!
好了
Right!
都跟我們去警局
You are all coming to the station with us.
我們只是找找樂子  警官
We're just having a bit of fun, Officer.
沒人想惹麻煩
No one's making any trouble.
那得讓法官來判斷
That's for the judge to decide.
-法官  -你以為呢
- Judge? - What did you think?
我們打打你們的手腕  就讓你們回家了
We're gonna slap your wrists and send you home?
我以前沒來過的
I've never been here before.
你這不來了  好
You're here now. Right!
拿上東西
Gather your things!
跟我們出來  臭變態  出來
You're coming with us, you dirty perverts. Out.
-出來  快  -快走  噁心的混蛋
- Get out! Move it! - Come on, you filthy sods.
-快走  -上去  上車
- Come on, you lot. - Pack it in. Get in the van.
別打了
Sort it out.
-給  親愛的  -謝謝
- There we are, my dear. - Oh, thank you.
好  親愛的
Yes, darling.
謝謝
Thank you.
可能得要會兒
There might be a moment.
我見過那女僕了
I met the maid.
她把莫德擺弄於股掌之中
She has Maud wound around her little finger.
那我們得搞清楚原因
Then we need to know why.
我很期待  先生們
Well, I'll look forward to it, gentlemen.
-謝謝  陛下  -大人
- Thank you, Your Majesty. - Milord.
怎麼了  赫克瑟姆
What is it, Hexham?
陛下  是這樣的
Well, Your Majesty, it's this.
我剛得知  赫克瑟姆夫人
I've just learned that Lady Hexham
懷了我們的第一個孩子
is expecting our first child.
這太好了
But that's wonderful news.
我們還沒想告訴別人
We're not telling anyone quite yet,
但我覺得您會想知道
but I thought you'd be interested.
是的  恭喜你
And so I am. Congratulations.
問題是  先生
The-the thing is, sir,
預產期大概是
it's due to be born around the time
我和王子要出發的時候
the prince and I will be setting off on tour.
太好了
Excellent.
務必讓他知道此事
Please make it register with him.
幫他理解建立真正的家庭生活的
Help the prince to understand what it means
意義所在
to have a real family life.
你可以做他的好榜樣
You can be such an example to him.
你肯定行
I know it.
那好  我們直說吧
Very well. Let's get to the point.
羅伯特是我父親這邊  跟我關係最近的親戚
Robert is my nearest relation on my father's side.
對
He is.
但他不能做我的繼承人
But he will not be my heir.
這就是了
And there we have it.
誰會是繼承人呢  你能告訴我們嗎
Who will be? Can you tell us?
露西•史密斯  我的女僕
Lucy Smith, my maid.
什麼  你瘋了嗎
What? Are you out of your mind?
沒有  我心裡有數
No. And I know what I'm doing.
恰恰相反  你顯然是瘋了
On the contrary, you're-you're clearly insane.
你該進精神病院
You should be in an asylum.
你就是如此  敢抵觸你一句
How like you. A word of resistance,
你就利刃出鞘
and you slash with your saber.
史密斯小姐該慶倖我沒有利刃
It is lucky for Miss Smith that I do not own a saber.
你真是你自己的選擇咯
So, this is truly your choice?
露西照顧了我多年
Lucy has taken care of me for many years.
我想表示感激
I wish to show my gratitude.
用家族宅邸嗎
With the family house?
用家族地產嗎
With the family estate?
你真該穿束身衣
You belong in a straitjacket.
把你的女僕當血親
To treat your maid as a blood relation
這有違英國的一切傳統
is to unpick every fiber of the English way of life.
真是傻話
What piffle you talk.
行了  我們不必吵起來
Please, there is no need to argue.
我從不吵
I never argue.
我只是解釋
I explain.
接受吧  維奧蕾特
Face it, Violet,
我反正也會比你活得長
I'll outlive you anyway,
你不必再為此操心了
so it need trouble you no further.
現在  我得去服侍陛下了
And now... I must attend Her Majesty.
巴格肖夫人大獲全勝
Game, set and match to Lady Bagshaw.
只要我是裁判就別想
Not while I'm the umpire.
我們喝了幾杯酒  巴羅先生就想去
We had a few drinks, and Mr. Barrow thought
戲弄下那些基佬  僅此而已
it'd be fun to play a trick on the queers, that's all.
他也才進去了五分鐘
He was only in there for five minutes.
跟另一個男人跳探戈
Dancing the tango with another man.
得了  警長  就是個玩笑
Come on, Sergeant, it was a joke.
但真讓人噁心
Turns your stomach, though.
那就好
Relieved to hear it.
是啊  如果我是那種人  我寧可去死
Yeah, I'd rather be dead if I thought I was one of them.
但我該怎麼跟伯爵交待
But what can I say to the earl?
什麼伯爵
What earl?
格蘭瑟姆伯爵
The Earl of Grantham.
巴羅先生是他的管家
Mr. Barrow is his butler.
當然  你會需要我出示身份證明
Of course, you'll want to see proof of my identity.
-是你把我救出來的嗎  -不是
- Was it you who got me out? - No.
是乘月光下凡的仙女
The good fairy came down on a moonbeam.
你怎麼知道我去哪了
How did you know where I'd gone?
房東說的
The landlord told me.
我在外面等著  然後跟來了這裡
Waited outside, followed you here.
然後我向警長出示了我的名片
Then I showed the sergeant my card,
似乎就把一切擺平了
and that seemed to settle things.
"皇家內務府"
"The royal household."
他肯定可高興了
He must have loved that.
我...
I'm a...
我真是太傻了
I'm afraid I've been a silly boy.
你今後可得更小心些了  巴羅先生
You just need to be a bit more circumspect in future, Mr. Barrow.
請您脫下來  小姐
Could you please remove it, milady,
但別動別針
leaving the pins in place?
你走前真能修好嗎
Can you really get it done before you go?
-不太可能吧  -她能做好的
- I don't see how. - She'll finish it.
-是吧  -我會盡力的
- Won't you? - I'll do my best.
你肯定能行
I'm sure you'll manage.
對了  我可能知道客廳的丘比特
By the way, I think I know what happened to the cupid
是去哪了  小姐
from the drawing room, milady.
是嗎  不見了嗎
Really? Was it missing?
您的裙子早上就能改好  小姐
Your dress will be ready in the morning, milady.
謝謝
Thank you.
不知你怎麼說服她的
I don't know how you persuaded her.
她其實挺好的  如果瞭解她的話
She's nice, really. When you get to know her.
還有別的事嗎
Is there anything else?
只想說你真是天才
Only to say that you're a genius.
-晚安  -晚安
- Good night. - Good night.
我恐怕沒能改變什麼
I'm afraid I didn't get anywhere.
那沒辦法了
Well, that's that.
就因為國王
Just because the king
不認為育兒跟男人有關
doesn't see that a man has any part to play in childbearing.
他確實這麼想
Well, he doesn't.
但按說他該理解當爹的不想離開
But you'd think he'd know that one likes to be around.
你不能直接拒絕他嗎
You can't just tell him no?
親愛的  我可是本國的高級貴族之一
Darling, I'm one of the senior peers in the land.
你以為那意味了什麼
What do you think that means?
你以為我擔負了怎樣的職責
What do you think I'm sworn to?
巴格肖夫人
Lady Bagshaw,
您呼叫女僕前  我能跟你說句話嗎
could I have a word before you ring for your maid?
露西知道你是她媽媽嗎
Does Lucy know that you're her mother?
她知道
She does.
很多年來  我都說我是她的教母
For years, I said I was her godmother,
但她18歲時  我說出了真相
but I told her the truth on her 18th birthday.
傑克死時  她多大
How old was she when Jack died?
六歲
Six.
那之前她一直跟傑克和她母親住
She'd lived with Jack and his mother until then.
後來我讓她住進了我家
But I took her into the house,
去村裡的學校上學
and she went to the village school
最終  她成了我的女僕
until, eventually, she became my maid.
如果她做了你的養女
I suppose if she'd been your ward,
大家就會猜到了
people would have guessed.
是啊
Exactly.
誰會注意一個僕人呢
Who takes notice of a servant?
我把她藏在了光天化日下
I hid her in plain sight.
你愛傑克•史密斯嗎
Did you love Jack Smith?
每個人都該擁有一次真正的愛情
Everyone should know a total love at least once.
傑克就是我的愛
Jack was mine.
我丈夫很乏味
My husband was very dull, you know?
他不壞  但
He wasn't a bad man, but...
但也不是很聰明
but he wasn't a clever one, either.
他死後  傑克來見我
Then he died, and Jack came to see me,
我們就此開始
and it began from there.
好大膽
How daring.
我知道聽上去很衝動
I know it sounds reckless,
但我懷孕時都39了
but I was 39 when I got pregnant.
我以為我不孕呢
I thought I was barren.
我當然知道我不能告訴我父親
Of course, I knew I couldn't tell my father, so...
我就去了美國
I went to America.
他們肯定覺得那很瘋狂
They must have thought that wild.
他們可不知道是有多瘋狂
Well, little did they know how wild it really was.
但你跟傑克很幸福嗎
But you were happy with Jack?
非常幸福
Oh, very.
他死前我們度過了10年
We had ten years together before he died.
如果我是個勇敢的人  我會嫁給他的
I'd have married him if I'd had the courage.
但我軟弱
I was weak.
但你是沒見過我父親
But you never knew my father.
內務府一直不許你說出此事吧
I suppose royal service kept you silent on the subject.
是啊
Yes.
可以這麼說
In a way.
但其實就是我膽小
But it was cowardice, really.
而通過讓露西做我的繼承人
Now, by making Lucy my heir,
就算是邁出第一步了
I will have taken the first step.
你得馬上告訴維奧蕾特
You must tell Violet at once.
-我不能  -你錯了
- I couldn't. - You're wrong.
一旦她知道了真相  就能理解你的計畫
As soon as she knows the truth, she'll fathom your plans
不再跟你作對
and cease to fight you.
僕人們今晚似乎都很開心
The servants seem to be enjoying themselves tonight.
尤其是莫斯利
Especially Molesley.
皇家僕人都哪去了
What happened to the royal team?
說來話長  小姐
It's a long story, milady.
但您說對了  我們是很開心
But you're right. We did have fun.
很高興大家都一切順利
Well, I'm glad it's gone well for everyone.
但我恐怕受不了再來一次了
But I don't think I could face doing it again.
還沒完事呢
You're not finished yet.
還有哈伍德舞會呢
You've still got the ball at Harewood.
是啊  但如果出了事  可就不再怪我們了
Yes, but it won't be our fault if anything goes wrong.
這話好喪氣啊
That's not very cheerful.
這幾天讓我思考
The last few days have made me think.
我們還該繼續嗎
Should we really go on with it?
我們宅裡的人手本就太少了
We're running the house with too few people as it is,
而半數現在在的  很快又會離開
and half of those here now will leave soon.
您什麼意思  小姐
What are you saying, milady?
是不是該放棄了
Isn't it time to chuck in the towel?
很多人都放棄了
Lots of people have.
您是說  離開唐頓嗎
You mean... leave Downton?
我們可以賣了它做學校
We could sell it for a school
或老人院什麼的
or an old people's home or something.
買棟別墅  一小塊地皮
And buy a manor house with a modest estate
過正常生活
and live a normal life.
那真是您想要的嗎
Is that what you want?
我想要一切不再這麼艱難
I want everything to stop being such a struggle.
僕人們會留下嗎  農場能收回投資嗎
Will the staff stay? Will the farms pay?
我們怎麼處理屋頂
What are we going to do about the roof?
我在大雨裡擺椅子時
When I was putting up the chairs in the rain,
我一直在想  "我在幹什麼"
I kept thinking, "What am I doing?"
我告訴您  小姐
I'll tell you what you're doing, milady.
您提供了一個中心給在這裡工作的人
You're making a center for the people who work here.
還有這村子
For this village.
這個郡
For the county.
唐頓莊園是這個社區的中心
Downton Abbey is the heart of this community,
您在維繫它
and you're keeping it beating.
所以你覺得我們該堅持下去
So you think we should battle on?
只要您還一息尚存
While there's blood in your veins.
史密斯小姐
Miss Smith.
她安頓好了嗎
Is she settled for the night?
說驚魂未定還差不多
She's more rattled than settled.
而且我說對了
And I was right.
他們是為我吵了起來
There was an argument. It was about me.
我聽格蘭瑟姆伯爵說
I hear from Lord Grantham
她打算讓你過上更好的生活
she's planning to alter your life for the better.
他說格蘭瑟姆老夫人準備好殊死一搏了
He says Old Lady Grantham was up in arms.
我能想像
I can imagine.
你有權享有這份好運嗎
Are you entitled to your good luck?
你知道她為什麼這麼做嗎
Do you know why she's doing it?
我知道
I do.
我覺得很公平
And I think it's fair.
那祝你一切順利  好好利用你的好運
Go forward in health, and use your luck wisely.
我覺得你能理解
I have such a feeling that you can understand
我在想什麼  雖然其他人不能
what's going on inside my head when no one else does
永遠也不能
or ever could.
我會懷念跟你聊天的
I'll miss our talks.
你願意給我寫信嗎
Would you like to write to me?
我隨時可以給你提供安慰
I could always provide a shoulder.
可以嗎
May I?
真的
Really?
如果你願意我會很高興的
I should be pleased and flattered if you would.
我現在該道晚安了  布蘭森先生
And now I think it's time to say good night, Mr. Branson.
晚安  史密斯小姐
Good night, Miss Smith.
敬唐頓和我美麗妻子
Here's to the triumph of Downton
大獲全勝
and my beautiful wife.
敬你們能成功做到
Oh, here's to all of you who brought it off.
敬卡森先生能割捨原則
Here's to Mr. Carson for swallowing his principles.
我今晚是睡不著了
Well, I shan't sleep a wink tonight.
敬王后陛下可憐莫斯利先生
And here's to Her Majesty for taking pity on Mr. Molesley.
我有那麼一刻還以為自己要被處決了
For a moment there, I thought I was headed for the Tower.
你不是要對他們改變看法了吧
You're not coming round to 'em, are you?
她真的很好心  黛西
It was decent of her, Daisy,
她本可為此鬧得很難看
when she could have let it spoil things.
不是每個人都像羅伯斯庇爾
Not everyone's like Robespierre.
我們敬國王和王后吧
Let's hear it for the king and queen.
敬國王和王后
The king and queen.
我有話要對你說  黛西
I've got to tell you something, Daisy.
是我砸壞了泵
It was me that broke the pump.
我也不知道我是怎麼了
I don't know what I was doing.
我就是嫉妒得發狂
I was just in a jealous rage.
-為什麼  -因為你跟那個水管工眉來眼去
- Why? - It was that plumber you made eyes at.
讓我氣得發昏
I just saw red.
然後我意識到因為我  他又回來了
And then when I realized I'd brought him back to the house,
我都要氣瘋了
I went nearly mad.
我才沒跟他眉來眼去
I did not make eyes.
我是喜歡他  但也沒別的了
I liked him, but there was nothing more to it.
我現在覺得好傻
Well, I feel a fool now.
你企圖破壞英國國王的來訪
You tried to wreck the visit of the King of England.
你可能被解雇
You risked being sacked,
可能大禍臨頭
you risked ruin...
就因為愛我嗎
...just for the love of me?
我...被情感沖昏了頭
I just... my feelings took over.
我沒別的好說了
That's all I can say.
你能原諒我嗎
Can you forgive me?
原諒你
Forgive you?
安迪  如果我有這膽子  我也會那麼做的
Oh, Andy, I'd have done it myself if I'd had the nerve.
你不懂這意味著什麼嗎
Don't you see what it means?
我們很像
We're alike, you and I.
我們為重要的事充滿激情
Full of passion for what matters.
我還以為你很容易滿足
I thought you were easily satisfied,
但我現在知道你不是的
but I see now you're not.
那我們就可以一起為更好的世界奮鬥了
So we can fight our way to a better world together.
我覺得我沒有為你幫我的忙好好表示感激
I'm not sure I've shown enough gratitude for what you did.
我們這樣的人可得團結點
We have to stick together, men like us.
問題就在這裡
That's the point.
我不認識我這樣的人
I don't know any men like I am.
我從未單純跟我這樣的人聊聊天
I've never just talked to someone like me.
我們這不在聊天嗎
Well, we're talking now.
這感覺很棒
And it feels good.
就是兩個人  聊聊天
Just to be two blokes, having a chat,
不用努力去融入
not trying to fit in for once.
我們都得為活著而苟且
Well, we all have to do what we must to get by.
但是的  能做兩個普通人的感覺真好
But yeah. Feels good to be two ordinary blokes.
我們有一日會被理解嗎
Will they ever see it our way?
我不知道
I don't know.
50年前  誰能想到人會能飛上天
50 years ago, who'd have thought man could fly?
貝茨太太
Mrs. Bates?
裙子好了
Well, here's the dress.
你走前我們會試一下
We can try it before you leave.
不必  肯定合身
No need. It'll fit.
這是你要的東西
Those are the things you wanted.
你為什麼這麼做  勞頓小姐
Why do you do it, Miss Lawton?
你就不鬧心嗎
Doesn't it ever worry you
這房子裡的每張桌子上
that on each table in this house,
都有你一年的工資
there's an ornament that you couldn't buy
也買不起的東西
with a year's wages?
那你怎麼想的呢
And what's your answer?
就因為不是每個人都買得起
Because everyone can't have them,
-所以沒人該擁有它們嗎  -不
- no one should have them? - No.
我想的是  "憑什麼我不能擁有
My answer is, "Why can't I have them?
至少是幾樣"
Or some of them."
別擔心  他們不會在意我拿的東西
Don't worry, they won't miss what I take.
恐怕一百個人裡都不會有一個
I doubt there's more than one in 100
注意到東西沒了
would even notice they're gone.
但那些東西不是你的  勞頓小姐
But they're not yours, Miss Lawton.
永遠也不是
And they never will be.
我勸你別再這麼幹了
I'd give it up if I were you.
如果人們以為是王后手腳不乾淨呢
What if people were to think Her Majesty was light-fingered
因為她待過的每戶家庭裡都有東西丟失
if things go missing from every house she stays in?
你的建議留給想聽的人吧  貝茨太太
Keep your advice for someone who's interested, Mrs. Bates.
那些門真是太差勁了
Those doors play up something dreadful.
毫無理由就卡住了
They jam and stick for no reason.
大家都遭遇過
It's happened to everyone.
你們怎麼都沒去找我
Why didn't any of you look for me?
我以為看到你出去了  威爾森先生
I thought I'd seen you go out, Mr. Wilson.
我一定是看錯了
I'm afraid I was mistaken.
你還有一錯  忘記叫醒科貝特先生了
Just as you were mistaken in not waking Monsieur Courbet.
我們以為他出去了
We thought he'd gone out and all.
謝謝  休斯太太
Thank you, Mrs. Hughes.
麻煩再拿點橘子醬
A little more marmalade, if you please.
男僕今早來了電話
The footmen have telephoned this morning.
他們似乎是被騙去了倫敦
It seems it was a hoax that took them up to London.
-但誰會那麼做呢  -問得好
- But who would do that? - Who, indeed?
等我們到了哈伍德再調查吧
We can investigate when we get to Harewood.
最好小心  科貝特先生
I should be careful, Monsieur Courbet,
可別讓自己出醜
unless you enjoy ridicule.
-什麼  -昨晚的晚宴相當成功
- What? - I'd say the dinner was a success.
他們還表示了讚揚
They sent down their compliments,
肯定是很成功了
so I think it must have been.
那麼  何必繼續追究
Well, then, why call attention to it?
你覺得這會對你有好處嗎
Would you show to advantage in this story, do you think?
但如果我們被問到要怎麼說呢
But what do we say if we're asked?
就說是倫敦那邊搞錯了
There was a confusion in London.
科貝特先生是病了
Monsieur Courbet was ill.
如果我是你  就乾脆不提
If I were you, I wouldn't mention it.
除非他們問了
Not unless they bring it up.
是啊
Quite right.
你在這裡
There you are.
我到處找你
I've been looking everywhere.
怎麼了  親愛的
What's the matter, darling?
我能幫你什麼嗎
Is it something I can help with?
從昨晚來看  你做不了什麼
Judging by last night, I doubt it.
我只是想掌控我自己的生活
I just want to own my own life.
我想說出我的想法  做我想做的事
I want to say things that I think and do what I like.
-你現在不能嗎  -不能
- Don't you now? - No.
我整日招待那些讓我無聊的人
I spend my time entertaining people who bore me to death
只因他們有權跟我們同桌
because they're entitled to sit at our table.
我參加我沒想參加的委員會
I attend committees that I haven't chosen
因為他們選上了我
because they've chosen me.
我以前本來有我熱愛的工作  但現在沒了
I used to have a job that I loved, but not anymore.
現在我生孩子時  我丈夫都不會在場
And now my husband won't be there when I have a baby.
這是普通農婦都能享有的權利  可我沒有
The woman in the lodge is entitled to that, but I'm not.
提醒你一下
Early warning.
陛下準備走了
Their Majesties are getting ready to leave.
好的  老爺
Very good, milord.
親愛的  你怎麼了
Darling, what's the matter?
您幫不上的
Nothing you can help with.
不能讓我試試嗎
Can't I try?
我們該上去了
Oh, uh, we should go up.
陛下要走了
Their Majesties are on their way.
好
Oh, right.
來吧
Come on.
上去了
Up we go.
你要去倫敦了
So, you're off to London?
他們會把我送到車站
They'll drop me at the station.
希望我們可以保持聯繫
Well, I hope we can keep in touch.
我覺得我總算找到個朋友
I feel I've finally found a friend.
我是這樣嗎  巴羅先生
Is that what you found, Mr. Barrow?
朋友
A friend?
-陛下要走了  -謝謝
- Their Majesties are going. - Thanks.
我想給你這個
I want you to have this.
雖然不貴重  但我帶了很多年了
It's not much, but I've had it for years.
能讓你惦記著我
It'll remind you of me.
這才是最重要的  是吧
That's the point, isn't it?
再見之前  讓你能記著我
So you can think of me till we meet again?
謝謝
Thank you.
艾理斯先生
Mr. Ellis,
你得來了
you must come!
希望您在哈伍德會一切愉快  先生
I hope you enjoy your time at Harewood, sir.
我也希望能
Yes. I hope so, too.
今晚我們就能再見
It isn't really goodbye
所以這算不上道別
when we'll see you all this evening.
我們很期待舞會
We're looking forward to the ball.
哈伍德真是棟美麗的宅子
Harewood is such a wonderful house.
我們上車吧
Well, let's mount up, shall we?
-回頭見了  格蘭瑟姆  -是  陛下
- We'll see you later, Grantham. - Your Majesty.
好樣的  各位  我們回去吧
Well done, everyone. Shall we head back in?
瑪麗  你穿什麼去舞會
Mary, what are you wearing to the ball?
我不知道
Oh, I don't know.
卡森  皇家僕人昨晚是哪去了
Carson, what happened to the royal servants last night?
不好說  老爺
Hard to say, milord.
他們不見了
They sort of gave up the ghost.
反正你做得很好
Well, you managed splendidly.
但莫斯利要是沒唱那一出就好了
Although I could have done without Molesley's aria.
但還是謝謝僕人們挽救了大局
But please thank the staff for saving the day.
貝茨太太
Mrs. Bates?
-失陪  -能問你件事嗎
- Excuse me. - Can I ask you something?
你給科貝特先生下了什麼
What did you give Monsieur Courbet?
在他的茶裡下了貝克韋爾先生
A double dose of a sleeping draught
那裡買來的雙份安眠藥
from Mr. Bakewell's... in his tea.
我昨晚真是出醜了
I'm afraid I made rather a fool of myself last night.
我永遠不覺得你出醜的
You could never be a fool to me.
你真心的嗎
Do you mean that, really?
是的
I do.
我覺得你瞭解我的真心
And I think you know how much.
你是對的  派特莫太太
You're right, Mrs. Patmore.
我是該籌畫婚禮了
It's time I started to plan my wedding.
真不知你怎麼想了這麼久
Well, I don't know what took you so long.
我之前不確定  但我現在確定了
I wasn't sure before, but I am now.
那就好
Well, that's good to hear.
我好開心  派特莫太太
I'm happy, Mrs. Patmore.
我不常那麼說  但我真的開心
I don't often say that, but I am.
這一切讓你震驚了嗎
Are you very shocked by it all?
應該震驚  皇室來訪期間作弄宮廷僕人
I should be. Interfering with the palace staff on a royal visit--
而我也參與其中
and me part of it, to boot.
真不知我是怎麼了
I don't know what came over me.
但是呢
But?
他們活該  艾爾希
They had it coming to them, Elsie.
我們承認吧  他們太活該了
Let's face it, they had it coming in spades.
哎呦
Hello.
怎麼回事
What's this?
歡迎回來  塔伯特先生
Welcome back, Mr. Talbot.
你們好  卡森  休斯太太
Hello, Carson. Mrs. Hughes.
你們知道瑪麗小姐在哪嗎
Do you know where I'll find Lady Mary?
發生了這麼多事
After everything that's gone on,
她大概是去躺下了  先生
I should think she'll be lying down, sir.
他們肯定都是
They all will be.
聽上去不妙呢
Sounds ominous.
太好了  他趕上舞會了
That's nice that he's back in time for the ball.
謝天謝地  不用我們籌辦
And thank the Lord we don't have to organize it.
親愛的  你不知道我們經歷了什麼
Oh, darling, you don't know what we've lived though.
很抱歉我不能早點回來
I'm sorry I couldn't get here sooner.
最後一場會一開完  我就乘第一艘船回來了
It was the first ship after the last meeting, I promise.
沒事了  你現在回來了
Oh, never mind. You're here now.
我不用自己去參加舞會了
And I don't have to go to the ball alone
可憐巴巴地在一旁看著
like a sad little wallflower.
如果你答應跟我跳一整晚的舞  我才會去
Well, I'll only come if you promise to dance with me nonstop.
說定了
Oh, it's a deal.
-晚上好  -陛下
- Good evening. - Your Majesty.
莫德肯定帶來了
I suppose Maud has brought
那個狡猾的小狐狸精
that scheming little minx with her.
你再這麼下去
If you continue in this vein,
只會讓自己出醜
you will only make yourself look stupid.
-你什麼意思  -就那意思
- What-what do you mean? - What I say.
你有事瞞我嗎
Are you keeping something from me?
跟我來
Come with me.
什麼
What?
您怎麼不高興
Why aren't you happy?
我以為您會高興得發狂呢
I thought you'd be delirious.
如果你是真心的  我們當然很高興
Well, we are happy, if you mean it. Very.
但你要怎麼應付亨利
But how will you manage Henry?
改變我們對待彼此的方式
By altering the way we manage each other.
雖然不會容易
And it may not be easy,
但我已經決定要留在他身邊了
but I've decided that I'm staying with him.
我不懂是什麼讓你改了主意
I just don't understand what changed your mind.
是因為布蘭森先生說的
It was something Mr. Branson said
要想好什麼才最重要
about deciding what matters.
對於我  王權比我們都更重要
For me, the Crown matters more than any of us.
我可以處理好
I can make it work.
布蘭森  那個愛爾蘭共和黨人嗎
Branson? The Irish republican?
您知道不少嘛
Oh, you're well-informed.
我比你以為的知道得多
I'm better informed than you know.
是他說服你這麼做的
So, he persuaded you to do this?
我們在閱兵後聊了一會兒
Oh, we were talking after the parade.
他來了
Oh, there he is.
跟他說句好話吧  拜託
Say something nice. Please.
要知道  你不在可挺悶的
I have to say, it's been very quiet without you.
布蘭森先生
Mr. Branson.
在唐頓時我們真該多聊聊
I wish we had spoken more while we were at Downton Abbey.
-是嗎  先生  -是的
- Do you, sir? - Certainly.
據我所知  我有不止一個理由應當感激你
I believe I have more than one reason to be grateful to you.
不止一個
More than one.
那是怎麼回事
What was that all about?
回頭我單獨告訴你
I'll tell you when we're alone.
什麼叫不止一個
Why more than one?
她是誰
Who is she?
瑪麗公主
That's Princess Mary.
她昨天去唐頓參加了閱兵
She was at Downton for the parade yesterday.
你沒看到她嗎
Didn't you see her?
沒在閱兵上看到
Not at the parade.
但我之後喝下午茶時見到了她
But I saw her afterwards at the tea.
所以她也有繼承布朗普頓的權利
So, you see, she has Brompton blood,
雖然不太尋常
albeit from an unusual angle.
你怎麼早不說
Why did you not say this long ago?
感覺你可能不太好理解
It seemed too great a leap for you.
你把我當成什麼樣的人了
Well, who do you think I am?
沒出過村的老處女姨媽嗎
Some maiden aunt who's never left the village?
顯然不是
Obviously not.
別以為我贊成  我可不
Well, don't think I approve, because I don't.
但至少我理解了
But at least I understand.
史密斯小姐知道真相嗎
Does Miss Smith know the truth?
是的
Yes, she does.
等我回到家  我就另雇一個女僕
When I get home, I will hire another maid,
讓露西做我的伴侶
and Lucy can be my companion.
這合適多了
Well, that's much more suitable.
你恐怕不會高興
And I'm afraid you'll dislike it,
但她說  她和湯姆•布蘭森
but she says that she and Tom Branson
說好要通信了
have agreed to correspond.
不高興
Dislike it?
我願親自給他們舔郵票
I will lick the stamps myself.
你真不可思議  維奧蕾特
You are amazing, Violet.
你可沒贏
You haven't won, you know.
我不相信失敗
I don't believe in defeat.
但等你和露西
But we can hammer this out
回來住時  我們可以再商量
when you come back to stay, you and Lucy,
等你完成巡視職責了的
when you've finished your tour of duty.
你是說  我又是這家的一員了嗎
You mean I am once more a member of this family?
她說得對  布朗普頓你別指望了
She's right, you know. Brompton is gone.
你們都只能接受
And you must all learn to live with it.
我們還能要回來的
I think we can get it back.
至少為了湯姆
For Tom, at least.
所以我們需要那女孩回來這裡
That's why we need the girl back here.
維奧蕾特
Oh, Violet.
這麼多年了  你還是能令我震驚
After all these years, you still astonish me.
很好
Oh, good.
很高興我能出乎意料  而不是令人失望
I'm glad I'm a revelation and not a disappointment.
-這很重要  -是啊
- It's very important. - Quite right.
-他們來了  問問吧  -好
- Oh, there they are now. Do ask. - Ah, yes.
你來了  赫克瑟姆
There you are, Hexham.
很遺憾你不能隨王子出行了
I'm sad you can't be part of the prince's tour,
但我們可以另給你找事做
but we'll find something else for you to do.
-什麼  -先生  我不...
- What? - Sir, I-I didn't, um...
我能理解你為何不能去
I understood why not, uh,
王后向我解釋了
as soon as Her Majesty had explained it to me.
恭喜你們
Congratulations to you both.
你今晚好高興啊
You're looking very sunny tonight.
我很幸福  怎麼  讓你不爽嗎
I'm happy. Why? Does it bother you?
沒有  但告訴我  你對湯姆
No. But tell me, what are you playing at
和莫德表親著名的女僕打的什麼主意
with Tom and Cousin Maud's famous maid?
什麼意思
What do you mean?
我昨晚聽到你在飯桌上說的話了
I heard you at dinner last night.
你打的什麼主意
What are you up to?
你知道她將繼承布朗普頓莊園
You know she'll inherit the Brompton estate.
-媽媽告訴我了  -那麼
- Well, so Mama told me. - Well, then,
你難道不希望湯姆有體面的財產嗎
wouldn't you like Tom to have a proper establishment?
你可真狡猾
Oh, you devious cat.
他們會幸福嗎  您覺得呢
Will they be happy? Do you think they will?
我去跟奶奶說句話
Oh, I just want a word with Granny.
您還打算等多久
How long were you planning to wait
再告訴我們您週三究竟為什麼去了倫敦
before you told us why you really went up to London on Wednesday?
既然你問了  我還沒想好呢
Since you ask, I haven't decided.
如果我現在告訴你
So, if I tell you now,
你可以保證不說出去嗎
will you promise to keep it to yourself?
我保證
I promise.
好吧
Very well. I...
我幾周前做了體檢
I had some medical tests a few weeks ago,
我是去倫敦瞭解結果的
and I went up to London to hear the results.
-怎麼樣  -是這樣
- Yes? - And, uh,
我可能要活不久了
I may not have long to live.
也不會那麼快
It won't be too quick.
但當然了
But, of course,
倫敦的醫生永遠說不準
you can never get a London doctor to be precise.
-奶奶  -不
- Oh, Granny. - No.
不不
No, no.
親愛的  你的眼淚留給難過的事吧
My dear, save your tears for something sad.
這沒什麼好難過的
Th-There's nothing sad here.
我度過了優渥有趣的一輩子
I have lived a privileged and an interesting life,
現在
and now it's...
我該走了
it's time to go.
我能把我的家庭
I'm leaving the family
和我珍視的地方
and the place that I treasure
留給得力的人
in talented hands.
-爸爸一定會...  -不不
- Well, I know Papa will be... - Oh, no, no.
我不是指你父親
No, I don't mean your father.
我很愛他
I... No, I-I love him dearly.
但我是說你
No, I... I mean you.
你是唐頓的未來
You are the future of Downton.
但我好懷疑  奶奶
But I have such doubts, Granny.
我們還應該繼續嗎
Are we right to keep it all going
畢竟它所屬於的時代
when the world it was built for
在隨著時間遠去
is fading with every day that passes?
喬治和卡洛琳還會過那樣的生活嗎
Will George and Caroline still be living that life?
-我們現在的生活算是嗎  -不
- Are we living it now? - No, no.
我們祖先的生活跟我們的生活不同
Our ancestors lived different lives from us,
我們後代的生活也會不同
and our descendants will live differently again,
但唐頓莊園會是那生活的一部分
but Downton Abbey will be part of them.
沒有您會不一樣的
Won't be the same without you.
當然了
Of course it will.
你要從我這裡接手
You'll take over from where I left off.
你會成為那個嚇人的老太太
You'll be the frightening old lady
讓所有人保持水準
keeping everyone up to the mark.
多謝您誇獎了
Thank you very much.
你能做到的  親愛的
You will, my darling.
你能做得很好
And you'll do it wonderfully.
你是我能在這世上延續的最好的部分
You're the best of me that will live on.
萬歲
Hurrah.
奶奶  我好愛您
Oh, Granny, I love you so much.
好了
No, shh.
但您今晚來不要緊嗎
But should you be here tonight?
不會太累嗎
Won't you be worn out?
瑪麗  我餘下的日子
Oh, Mary, I can't spend the rest of my life
可能不能總被問"你感覺還好嗎"
in a shower of "How are you feeling?"
"你沒事吧"  不
and "Are you quite well?" Oh, no.
總之  我沒事  直到我有事
The point is... I'll be fine until I'm not.
就是這樣
That's all there is to it.
你在這裡呢
There you are.
開始跳舞了
The dancing's starting.
你可不能錯過
You mustn't miss it.
是啊  謝謝
No. Thank you.
謝謝
Thank you.
你會永遠與我們同在的  奶奶
You know, you'll always be with us, Granny.
在每幅畫裡看著我們
Staring from every picture,
在每本書裡教導我們
talking from every book,
只要唐頓還在
as long as the house stands.
聽上去好累人
Sounds very exhausting.
知道嗎
Do you know, I think...
我更想安息長眠呢
I should prefer to rest in peace.
走吧
Come on.
親愛的
Darling.
你想要什麼
What is it you want?
我們有共同點
We have things in common.
孩子  騎馬  比賽
The boys, horses, racing.
如果我們願意去尋找  肯定還有其他
And there must be more if we look for it.
我希望我們做朋友
I want us to be friends.
那就試試看吧
Well, we'll have to see.
不  親愛的
No, dear.
我們得改變
We'll have to change.
我們都得改變
Both of us.
怎麼會這樣的
How did that happen?
是您的功勞嗎  媽媽
Was it you, Mama?
您怎麼做到的
How did you do it?
簡單
Simple.
伯蒂去找了國王
Bertie asked the king.
我去找了王后
I asked the queen.
我真喜歡我們的冒險
I do love our adventures.
但結束時也很開心吧
But isn't it fun when they're over?
你怎麼來了
What are you doing here?
我想看跳舞
I wanted to see the dancing,
所以我想假借名義  說是給巴格肖夫人拿手絹來
so I thought I'd pretend I was bringing Lady Bagshaw a handkerchief.
如果需要  我可以替你拿給她
I can give it to her, if you'd like.
我希望你能跟我跳舞
I wish you could dance with me.
我有個問題問你
I've got a question for you.
你不會離開唐頓
You'd never want to leave Downton
去別處重新開始吧
and start up somewhere else, would you?
老實說
And tell me truthfully.
怎麼說起這個了
What brought this on?
告訴我嘛
Just tell me.
離開唐頓
Leave Downton?
我們都離不開這裡了吧
I think we're stuck with it, aren't we?
是啊
Yes.
我想是的
Yes, I believe we are.
我們不該走這個門
We shouldn't come out this way.
他們不會介意的
Oh, they won't mind.
這一次不要緊
Not this once.
他們走了  可唐頓還在
Well, they've gone, and Downton is still standing.
艾爾希  再過一百年
Elsie, a hundred years from now,
唐頓也還會在
Downton will still be standing.
卡勞利一家也還會在這裡
And the Crawleys will still be here.
那是絕對的
And that is a promise.
走著瞧吧  查理
We'll see, Charlie.
走著瞧吧
We'll see.